<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Caleb's spirit parallel'd in a sermon preach'd at the funeral of the late Mrs. Constancy Ward of East-Smithfield, London, at the meeting-house in Devonshire Square, April 7, 1697 / by Walter Cross ...</title>
            <author>Cross, Walter, M.A.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 126 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35171</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7257</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22527</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12233542</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12233542</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56657</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35171)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56657)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 913:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Caleb's spirit parallel'd in a sermon preach'd at the funeral of the late Mrs. Constancy Ward of East-Smithfield, London, at the meeting-house in Devonshire Square, April 7, 1697 / by Walter Cross ...</title>
                  <author>Cross, Walter, M.A.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 43 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.D. for Andrew Bell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bristol Public Library, Bristol, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ward, Constancy, d. 1697.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56657:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Caleb's Spirit Parallel'd, IN A SERMON Preach'd at the FUNERAL Of the Late Mrs. <hi>CONSTANCY WARD</hi> Of <hi>Eaſt-Smithfield, London;</hi> At the Meeting-houſe in <hi>Devonſhire Square, April</hi> 7. 1697.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Walter Croſs</hi> M.A.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Vitam aeternam non poſſidebunt qui reſurrectionem a morte Legem a Coelo negant.</l>
               <l>Vitam Deo non degunt.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON;</hi> Printed by <hi>J. D.</hi> for <hi>Andrew Bell</hi> at the Croſs-keys and Bible in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> near <hi>Stocks-market.</hi> 1697.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:56657:2"/>
            <pb n="iii" facs="tcp:56657:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Numb. XIV. 24.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>But my Servant <hi>Caleb,</hi> becauſe he had another Spirit with him, and hath followed me fully, him will I bring into the Land, whereinto he went, and his Seed ſhall poſſeſs it.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN <hi>Ver.</hi> 21. the Subject of this <hi>Chap.</hi> is propos'd, <hi>viz.</hi> the 10th Provocation or Temptation of God: one was for doubling their Tasks in <hi>Egypt;</hi> a 2d for the Danger at <hi>Pi-habiroth, Exod.</hi> 14. the door of Liberty; the 3d, which ſome count pregnant of 3, was about the <hi>Manna;</hi> a 4th for Water, and a 5th for Fleſh; a 6th for the Idolatrous Calf, <hi>Apis;</hi> a 7th for the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of their Journey; an 8th for <hi>Miriam</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi>'s murmuring at <hi>Kibroth hatavae,</hi> the Graves of the Luſters; and the 9th their Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Sabbath. This 10th is a Twin-temptation too, they will not go up when God commands to go in and poſſeſs the Land, and they will go when he forbids: and all theſe in one Year and four Months, <hi>ver.</hi> 33. with <hi>chap.</hi> 1.1. This 10th Rebellion is elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently deſcribed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.21. <hi>They forgat God their Saviour, who had done great things in</hi> Egypt, <hi>wonderful things in the Land of</hi> Ham, <hi>terrible things by the Red Sea: they deſpis'd the pleaſant Land, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd not his Word,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This Sedition is the moſt directly oppoſite of any to God's De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign as well as Command: <hi>Let us return to</hi> Egypt. 2ly. The moſt provoking, and aggravated after ſo many Miracles, ſo many Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations, and ſo many Pardons [Surely it's a falſe Notion in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, that a Believer never backſlides twice in the ſame Sin] it is too narrow Charity to ſend all to Hell that fell in the Wilderneſs. 3ly. The moſt univerſal Apoſtacy, 4 only excepted, <hi>Moſes, Aaron, Caleb</hi> and <hi>Joſhua.</hi> 4ly. The moſt furious, and yet moſt deliberative, Head and Heart are as much united in every Man as they were to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:56657:3"/>one another: they reaſon'd the Caſe, and heard the Arguments of the Spies on both Sides; they weep, from a Perſwaſion there was moſt Truth on the Ten's ſide, they conſult to chooſe a Captain, they ſpeak of ſtoning the few Diſſenters.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ver.</hi> 24. Yet <hi>Caleb</hi> is here excepted: But why alone? why not <hi>Moſes?</hi> or rather <hi>Joſhua?</hi> or both? I anſwer; 1ſt. <hi>Caleb</hi>'s Zeal ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears moſt in oppoſing the Rebels. 2ly. His Courage appears moſt in forwardneſs as a Spy, eſpecially, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 14. in viewing the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kims</hi> Country; he there (<hi>Joſhua</hi> being Judg) aſſumes the Work wholly to himſelf. 3ly. He was then Repreſentative to the chief Tribe <hi>Juda,</hi> the firſt in Honour, the moſt numerous in Multitude, 186400, <hi>Ephraim</hi> about 40000, and <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> about 30000. 4ly. Each of them have their Rewards apart; <hi>Moſes</hi> was chief Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, <hi>Joſhua</hi> was his Succeſſor, and was made a Knight or a Baron on this very Envoy by <hi>Moſes;</hi> of <hi>Hoſea (ch.</hi> 13.) made <hi>Joſhua,</hi> as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> of <hi>Abram.</hi> But <hi>Caleb</hi> continues a private Perſon, in a plebei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Condition, all his Days, tho he died the oldeſt and ableſt Man; the moſt numerous, honourable, and richeſt Family of all <hi>Iſrael</hi> was his at laſt. This Difficulty about the Text being remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the next thing in order is to divide, or rather to obſerve its Parts as divided already by the ſame Authority that indited it
<note n="*" place="bottom">There is as much (and more, that being granted) to be ſaid for the Syntactical Uſe of the Points, than for their Antiquity: the Uſe is great, for they leave not one Verſe in all the Old Teſtament doubtful in Conſtruction, or arbitrary in Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. So the Uſe of the 34 Accents, is next to that of the Letters and Vowels, <hi>ex. gr. Gen.</hi> 10.21. The Brother of <hi>Japhet</hi> the Elder —֥— joins <hi>Japhet</hi> and <hi>Elder:</hi> ſo older than <hi>Shem, viz.</hi> 2 Years, for <hi>Noah</hi> begot one of them at 500, but <hi>Shem</hi> at 502, <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.10. <hi>Judg.</hi> 1.13. the Son of <hi>Kenaz, Brother of</hi> Caleb, <hi>the Younger; Caleb</hi> and <hi>Younger</hi> ſtand juſt as <hi>Japhet</hi> and <hi>Elder;</hi> but there is —֖— dividing them; ſo <hi>Kenaz</hi> is younger. Obſerve further, that <hi>Kenaz</hi> and <hi>Caleb</hi> are join'd, elſe <hi>Oth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>l</hi> marries his Brother's Daughter.</note>. 1ſt. It is divided from the Context foregoing and following by way of Parentheſis; for they cohere, <hi>ver.</hi> 23, and 25. thus, <hi>None of the Rebels ſhall ſee it:</hi> My Preſence ſhall not protect nor conduct them as before. <hi>Now ſince the Amalekites and a Colony of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naanites dwell in the Valley,</hi> juſt by you, <hi>to morrow be gone,</hi> for they will fall upon you and deſtroy you
<note n="†" place="bottom">The Hebrew has no Marks for a Parentheſis, that fills up a whole Verſe; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Senſe is there need of it: but for 4 or 5 words it has, tho obſerv'd in no Grammar I know.</note>. 2ly. The greateſt diviſion
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:56657:3"/>of the Contents within this Parentheſis is between the Work and Reward, the Duty performed, and Bleſſing promiſed. 3ly. The Subdiviſion is thus; the firſt Member has three Parts, the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>Caleb,</hi> his Spirit, <hi>Singular,</hi> his Practice, <hi>Full:</hi> the 2d Member has two Parts; the Bleſſing promiſed, the individual Land he cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragiouſly ſpied out, whoſe Inhabitants ſo cow'd the Spirits of the reſt; and 2ly. the Entail of that Bleſſing to his Seed. So theſe with the Particles of Connection afford 6 ſeveral Subjects of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, which I ſhall explain and apply as briefly as poſſible.</p>
            <p>The firſt occurring Part is the Perſon: <hi>But as to my Servant Caleb,</hi> he is propoſed, and by a —֗— diſtinguiſh'd from the following Words, as one who abſtractly from what follows deſerves Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration; and thorough pauſing on it by Direction, I find this viſible Obſervation, <hi>That it is not Publickneſs of Perſons by Office, their Honourableneſs by many and great Titles, their Riches, or the Greatneſs of their Actions, tho good too, that monopolizes the Honour of ſtanding laſting Monuments of Praiſe, or the Precedency of being ſingl'd out for Patterns of a Life acceptable to God. Naaſſon,</hi> to whom <hi>Caleb</hi> was grand Uncle, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.4. was the Duke of <hi>Judah, Numb.</hi> 1.7. and Reaſon good: for though <hi>Caleb</hi> was the older Man, yet of the younger Family, being 3d Son of <hi>Hezron,</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 2.9. <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s Name is changed, though it ſignified honourably before, to wit, <hi>Salvation:</hi> but <hi>Caleb</hi> ſignifieth a Dog, or one led in a String, from <hi>Cabal,</hi> yet muſt have no better all his Days: and the Epithet added, <hi>my Servant,</hi> except what is hid in the Relation <hi>my,</hi> is of no better note; a Slave, one bought with Money, whoſe Life is in his Maſter's Power, one liable to beating or Ignominy; <hi>pone Crueem ſervo.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> differ as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a Slave and a Miniſter. On which the great <hi>Gerard</hi> has this Note: <hi>Paul,</hi> ſays he, calls himſelf the Servant of Jeſus Chriſt, or Slave, from the Calling to his Office, not from the Work; for he calls himſelf, Miniſter, Steward, Ambaſſador, in that reſpect; but from the Title Chriſt had to him, and his Work: Chriſt had the Title of Conqueſt; he was a Slave of War, he came <hi>ſub Gladio,</hi> going to <hi>Damaſcus.</hi> 2ly. the Title of Purchaſe; he was not his own, nor any thing could he call his Property: Chriſt paid the Price of precious Blood for him, he coſt him more than Silver and Gold could be any Standard to, or Meaſure
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:56657:4"/>in Value of. Such a Slave was <hi>Caleb,</hi> a Son of <hi>Abraham,</hi> brought to the Foot of God, following him like a Dog; Name and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per agreeing, <hi>following him fully.</hi> This is one Reaſon why I have choſen this Parallel of <hi>Caleb</hi> and the Deceaſed Mrs. <hi>Ward:</hi> as <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi> illuſtrates Princes by Parallels, I by Divine Warrant may ſet forth a Perſon mean in the Heraldry of the World, yet precious, honourable in the Sight of God: and it is to encourage you mean Perſons, poor in the World, rich in Faith, not to be diſcouraged from ſerving God, his Church or People, with the ſcanty Talents and ſmall things that lie within the Compaſs of your Power or Station; it will bring in as rich a Reward, and as illuſtrious Honour, as if it were of 10000 times more Value: it's not the Greatneſs, but Goodneſs, not the Sumptuouſneſs, but Sincerity of Actions, renders them acceptable to God: he has a Diary for <hi>Dorcas</hi>'s Coats ſhe uſed to make for the Poor, for <hi>Nathaniel</hi>'s ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Prayers under the Tree: a Cup of cold Water given to one under the Name of a Diſciple, ſhall not loſe its Reward; nor the Widow's Mite caſt into the ſacred Treaſury eſcape the watchful Eye of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. He will bottle up every Tear that drops from a penitent Eye; the Widow's Cake and Cruiſe, the Shunamite's Table, Stool, Bed, and Candleſtick muſt have Monumental Room in ſacred Records for ever; as Chriſt ſaid of the Woman who poured the Ointment on his Head, Mat. 26. <hi>Whereſoever this Goſpel ſhall be preached in the whole World, there ſhall alſo this, that this Woman hath done, be told for a Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial of her.</hi> And not only Actions immediately terminating on Chriſt ſhall be recorded, but alſo a Servant <hi>Elizer</hi>'s Fidelity to his Maſter <hi>Abraham;</hi> and old <hi>Deborah Rebecca</hi>'s Nurſe for her Faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and tender Care in the Family, ſhall not only have her Duſt mingled with the Tears of the Family, but her Funerals recorded by the Spirit of God, <hi>Allon Baccuth,</hi> the Oak of weeping; and yet a Matter (apparently) of leſſer Moment than that, <hi>viz.</hi> of the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren that accompanied Chriſt to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> with their Boughs and Hoſannas. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8. the Praiſe from the Mouths of Babes, and Suck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings ſhall not only be hiſtorically reported, but prophetically foreſeen and foretold; it was in his Thoughts from all Eternity. Surely there is no leſs reaſon to think the good Deeds of this Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, her Pains and Travel Night and Day for many Years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſheltring the Exil'd, relieving the Diſtreſſed, hiding them
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:56657:4"/>in Danger, ſupplying them in want, venturing her Neck as <hi>Priſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilla</hi> and <hi>Aquila,</hi> not only for a <hi>Paul,</hi> but them that were not worthy to carry his Books with <hi>Timothy</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.13. Bring (not the Cloak, as our Engliſh hath it, but) the Desk, ſays <hi>Chryſ.</hi> Homil. 10. on this Ep. Others ſay the Bark uſed in the Eaſt for Paper, the proper Signification of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. A 3d ſay the Coverings, either by Syn. for Books, or becauſe of looſe Papers tied up in them. 4ly. In great Probability they who turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it Cloak, read <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Penula,</hi> for <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>. She was a true <hi>Phoebe, a Succour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of many, and my ſelf alſo,</hi> Rom. 16.2. She has had a Hand at many ſuch a Basket as that which help'd <hi>Paul</hi> over the Walls of <hi>Damaſcus.</hi> She has often hid <hi>David</hi>'s Spies with the good Woman of <hi>Baburim,</hi> and <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s with <hi>Rahab:</hi> ſhe will never want an Intereſt in the Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let Thread of Salvation from the Window, or Paſſover-Blood over the Door. And why may not the Mercy be of as ſpreading a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as <hi>Rahab</hi>'s, to all within the Houſe, to all her Father's and Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threns Houſhold, if they will come under the ſame Protecting Roof? I do not at all doubt that ſhe is now a canonized Saint, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt Influence, againſt the moſt powerful Anathema's, from Popiſh Authority. I ſhall end this Cloud of Witneſſes, as <hi>Paul, Heb.</hi> 11.34. with <hi>Rahab;</hi> for time would fail to heap together all the Inſtances of this kind, <hi>Job</hi>'s Perfection, <hi>Obedmelech</hi>'s viſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Jeremiah</hi> in the Dungeon, and bringing him up with old caſt Clouts under his Arm-pits, or <hi>Obadiah</hi>'s hiding the Prophets by fifties in Caves, and feeding them.</p>
            <p>Let us then ſuppoſe it ſufficiently prov'd or granted, that when Godlineſs is ſo powerful as to break forth in Acts of Charity, Courage, or publick Uſefulneſs, though in mean Perſons, it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves to be praiſed, to be ſolemnized with Memorials, to be imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated as a Pattern. And 2ly. let us ſuppoſe that this Perſon was ſo indued: what can be done for her? the Canon is now compleated, there is no more an Authentic Accompt from Heaven what Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are enfranchiz'd above: all Scripture, as it was wrote, was put in a Cheſt by the Side of the Ark, <hi>Deut.</hi> 31.24. Firſt the five Books of <hi>Moſes,</hi> called the Law, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.44. 2ly. What added by <hi>Samuel,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.25. and <hi>Joſhua</hi> 24.26. 3ly. It's likely <hi>Daniel</hi> came by <hi>Jeremiah</hi>'s Prophecy thus; that Cheſt being carried to <hi>Babylon,</hi> thither he ſent his MSS. as he had his Deeds of <hi>Anathoth,</hi> in Faith of a ſafe Return. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.2. unto them were
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:56657:5"/>thoſe Records committed, called by the Name of <hi>Scripture</hi> by way of Eminency in the New Teſtament; in their room now, the Gentile Churches being engrafted, are become the Pillars and Ground of all inſpired Truth, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. which was concluded by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles: All Writings ſince are Apocryphal, not put in that ſacred Place. <hi>Epiphan.</hi> de pond. <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. ſpeaking of Wiſdom and <hi>Siraci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,</hi> ſays, <hi>they are not in the Number of read Books,</hi> viz. every day ſome part; <hi>neither were they put in the Ark.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Joh. Damaſ. Panar. Dorſh. Huet.</hi> ſay <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is underſtood, and the Author had reaſon to know the Truth, his Father being a <hi>Samaritan.</hi>
               </note>.</p>
            <p>A ſecond Honour due, that ſhe was deprived of, was Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; two, may be, out of one Congregation was too much. It is well known her Guilt and her Siſter <hi>Gaunt</hi>'s were of the ſame kind [Guilt ſhall I call it, or Glory?] I am confident juſt Thoughts of that Affair would fright few that believe in Chriſt, and have a ſolid and clear Conſcience about the Cauſe they ſuffer for; a natural Death (as it is called, for all Death is violent) generally having more Pain and Tediouſneſs attending it, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten wanting that Exerciſe of Thought and Grace that is a grand Support to the tearing and rending, the Bruiſes and Breaches ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd under the parting of a Soul from a Body.</p>
            <p>Theſe Negatives may help us to conclude this Poſitive; That keeping within Bounds of Decency becoming her Station in the World, we cannot be eaſily guilty of tranſgreſſing in the Exceſs, eſpecially if we again conſider it was not a vertuous Action, but a Life of Actions. 2. The Actions were not mean, but great; by Exerciſe ſhe attained a Capacity of doing more for a Saint in Diſtreſs, and for more in number than it lay in the Power of Perſons having twenty times her Eſtate to do. We ſhould come ſhort of the Hypocrites, who build Tombs for dead Prophets when they perſecuted the Living, if we ſhould leave her without a Record in our Apocrypha's: we ſhould wrong our ſelves, if we keep not a living Idea of that Knowledg, Faith, Loving Temper, delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in doing Good, Sweetneſs in Converſation, a living Idea of that living Root of Grace and Vertue, daily fructifying and flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing in her, and deeply radicated through Humility, ſoon ſeen by all but her ſelf.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:56657:5"/>
            <p>In ſacred things the Church her Verdict is next to Chriſt's, a Prieſt's Lips is the Church's Tongue; this ſhe ought to have. 2. It's an Honour to have a great Train, many Followers; this ſhe deſerves. It would be the Happineſs of many ſelfiſh, covetous, narrow Spirits, to ſet her as a Pattern; her Publick Spirit has done more Good than they who have left 30000 <hi>l.</hi> at their Death to build Hoſpitals and Alms-houſes: beſides, ſhe had always in her Eye the <hi>eſpecially of the Houſhold of Faith,</hi> Love to Chriſt was the Spring; really it blows up a Flame in me to think of the Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to Jeſus Chriſt they
<note n="*" place="bottom">She and Mrs. <hi>Gaunt.</hi>
               </note> gloried in; the Longing for the Glory of his Kingdom, that rent their Breaſts; the Sagacity they ſearched the Scriptures with about it, allayed with the Patience and Prudence they moderated it with, and the Arms of ſpiritual Love they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced his poor and diſtreſſed Members. I hope the Reader will pardon this: I cannot but ſay what I have ſeen, heard, felt, and am able to anſwer for. Excepting one yet alive, (long may it be before ſhe meet with her due Honour) I think few Names have a more radicated Eſteem among Nobillity, Gentry, Miniſters, Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans of all kind in <hi>Scotland.</hi> Nor is the Savour of her Ointment con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained within, or confined to theſe 3 Kingdoms; <hi>Holland, Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, Sweedland, Denmark, Poland,</hi> have heard of her. But if we be wanting and deficient in our Duty below, all is now made up to her above: thoſe Angels that rejoice at a Soul's Converſion, how will they welcome her Entrance into Glory? All the Earth below is but a Point to the Countrey where her Fame will ſound, and her Glory ſhine. But I'm ſure ſhe'll be ſo much entranc'd in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miring and adoring that King of Glory, that ſhe will be a ſelf-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied Perſon amidſt all her Enjoyments. I was blam'd for not ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more to her Praiſe; indeed 'twas not for want of Matter, Thought or Words on this Subject; I had always a Heart to indite enough on this and like Subjects. But I ſhall proceed to the next Subject, leſt the next Perſon ſay my Pen wants a Bridle, if my Tongue had one.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing in the Words is the greateſt Particle of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nection in the Text, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> it's the Word from whence <hi>Jacob</hi> comes, the Word that ſignifies Heel, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. <hi>He ſhall bruiſe thy Heel.</hi> The Subject it affords to be diſcours'd on, is the relation between a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever's Work and Reward; it's tranſlated, <hi>becauſe he was of another
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:56657:6"/>Spirit.</hi> Indeed I find our Tranſlation favouring a Conditionality often without juſt Ground; <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.9, 10. <hi>The Lord will again rejoice over thee for good — If thou ſhalt hearken to the Voice of the Lord thy God:</hi> the Original is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>becauſe thou ſhalt hearken to the Voice:</hi> it is a Chain of Promiſes one upon another, not the Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion between Duty and Promiſe. And again in the ſame Verſe, <hi>If thou turn unto the Lord;</hi> it's <hi>becauſe thou ſhalt turn unto the Lord:</hi> and the grand Reaſon follows, <hi>Ver.</hi> 11, 12. from the preventing Grace of God, bringing the Commandment nigh to them, which is Old-Teſtament-Language for being mix'd with Faith in the Heart. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. <hi>Paul</hi> calls it the Word of Faith, and a Word about Goſpel-Righteouſneſs, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Word revealing Chriſt's going to Hell for us, or bearing equivalent Sufferings, the Curſe of the Law; the Word revealing Chriſt's going to Heaven for us, ſatisfying Divine Juſtice, and appeaſing Divine Anger, as God is the Rector of the World by the firſt Adamical Conſtitution. This Word being engrafted in the Heart by Faith, becomes a Spring of obeying the Commands of God; and both together ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the Soul an harmonious tun'd Inſtrument for Joy, and amia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for Delight. There is a double Cover in the Text: I might in prudence hide my Opinion in this Affair, in a Day, or rather Night of Controverſy, which is more proſecuted by Paſſion than Pains to underſtand that neceſſary Queſtion. One is the Word that is as often a Noun as a Particle, and ſignifies either the conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial End of Means, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.33, 112. <hi>Keep thy Statutes even unto the end:</hi> ſo this will be the Senſe, <hi>The end of his being of another Spirit, and following me fully, ſhall be my bringing him into the Land,</hi> &amp;c. Or, 2ly. It ſignifies the Courſe and Walk of a Perſon; <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.8. the <hi>Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps</hi> of the Flock; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 56.6. they mark my <hi>Steps:</hi> ſo this will be the Senſe, <hi>The Courſe and Walk of my Servant</hi> Caleb <hi>was from another Spirit that was with him, for he follow'd after me.</hi> A 2d might be the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; it was not pardon of Sin, or Inheritance among the Saints in Heaven, but a Part of, or Portion in the Land of <hi>Canaan.</hi> But the Difficulty in point of Merit, conſiſts not meerly in what Proportion there may be between Work and Reward, but alſo in the Relation and Proportion between the Perſons; <hi>Caleb</hi> could not merit one Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of Land from his <hi>God.</hi> I ſhall therefore out of Choice give my Opinion in the Affair: and 1ſt, That there is a near Connection between Holineſs and Happineſs, is without all Controverſy; and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:56657:6"/>the Agreement in that one Point (that <hi>without Holineſs no Man ſhall ſee the Lord;</hi> whoſoever <hi>names Jeſus,</hi> as pretending to an Intereſt in him, <hi>muſt depart from Iniquity</hi>) would and ſhould allay diſturbing and dividing Paſſions about the Point. But that intolerable Extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of counting Sin a Diſeaſe of meer natural Infirmity, and hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God for its Author, as much as he is the Author of judicial Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, or fatherly Chaſtiſement, deſerves Exilement from Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Society, as well as Excommunication from Sacred, it having the ſame abſurd Conſequences with Atheiſm attending it: for the Belief, or Unbelief rather, of the Non-exiſtence of a God, and of his not being offended with Sin, or morally ſwaying no Scepter, diſtributing no Rewards or Puniſhments by the Meaſures of moral Laws, are of the like Tendency, and render a Man liable to all Temptations: Robbery, Murder, or Adultery, under the probable proſpect of Advantage and Pleaſure, with Secrecy or Impunity, muſt be his common Trade; therefore the Diſcovery of his Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents is a juſt Ground of driving him from all Civil Society.</p>
            <p>But both by Scripture and Reaſon, we are not only convinc'd of the Neceſſity of the Connection, but the ſeveral Joints and Links of that Chain or Relation are revealed to us: (1.) Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively; there is not, nor cannot be the Relation of a moral Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, not in Sinners, not in <hi>Adam</hi> when innocent, not in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels. Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> moſt Orthodoxly ſays, the Doctrine is blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous to think that meer Nothing form'd into a Being, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by indebted for working or ſerving Faculties or Capacities, that its putting them in exerciſe, or that the Fruits and Effects of their Growth, ſhould as much oblige God, as the Subject of them is oblig'd to God. (2.) There is not the Relation that is purely fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deral by virtue of a Promiſe; If thou live holily without Spot, thou ſhalt be happy; that was Man's Condition before Sin in the Covenant of Works: There is not, nor cannot be any ſuch thing in the Covenant of Grace, God having to do therein with guilty Rebels, who have neither Power nor Will to change the Temper of their Minds. Nor (3.) Is there the Relation of Merit, by reaſon of our Works having an Intereſt in Chriſt, as the Papiſts phraſe it, <hi>tinct a ſanguine Chriſti;</hi> tho we, and all we do, are acceptable to God on that Score: for meriting on that Bottom ſuppoſes this, that though we cannot merit at the Hand of God without him, yet we can merit at his Hand; and that is of equal Abſurdity with
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:56657:7"/>the former, for there is no Proportion between our Service to him, and his for us; he needs not ſuch Service at our Hands, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires it, nor could we perform it if he did. The Dignity of his doing and ſuffering was from his Deity: We have nothing in us proportion'd to his Humanity; we are as much his by the Title of Redemption, as God's by Creation, ſo all we can do is due.</p>
            <p>But though theſe are juſtly laid aſide, the Connection is ſtronger than a threefold Cord that is not eaſily broken: for there is, firſt, a natural Connection, Heaven grows upon Love to God, Hell up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Hatred, Happineſs upon Holineſs, as ſutably and naturally as the Fruit, Leaves, and Branches of a Tree grow from the Root or Seed of its kind: <hi>Be not deceived, God is not mocked; for what a Man ſows, that ſhall he alſo reap.</hi> A Man by ſowing the Seed of Darnel, Thiſtles, or Nettles, may as ſoon and as truly expect a brave Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt of Wheat or Barley, as a Man with an habitual wicked Life may expect Heaven for the ſake of Jeſus Chriſt. (2.) There is the Relation between Means and End, Preparation and Poſſeſſion, a Journey homeward, and Reſt at home, to him that's abroad. Suppoſe one ſhould freely ranſom a Slave from <hi>Algiers,</hi> he can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver enjoy his Privileges, Poſſeſſions, and Relations in his own Countrey, without the Pains and Fatigue of a Sea-Voyage, the Danger of the Waves and Billows of the Bay of <hi>Biſcay.</hi> Suppoſe one freely give an Eſtate, or a Place of Honour at Court to a Beggar or Stranger, he can never reap the Fruit of it without Pains, he muſt fit and prepare himſelf for it. (3.) The Phraſes of Connecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on are of a legal Tenour, by reaſon of the Remunerableneſs of the Matter from the Tenour of the old Covenant; as we ſee the New Teſtament delights in Old-Teſtament-Phraſe: for inſtance, <hi>buried with him in Baptiſm,</hi> the Jewiſh Way of baptizing being burying-like. So what is now rewarded of Grace, retains the old Phraſe it had when it was by a Covenant of Works. (4.) There is a Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with reſpect to the Subject: to ſuch and ſuch Works are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed rich and everlaſting Rewards, becauſe he who only can do them, has a Right and Title to the Reward by the Promiſe and Grace of God. (5.) There is a Relation in reſpect of Chriſt, and our being in him. There was a Proportion between Works and Reward in the Mediatorial Covenant, and therein he is conſidered as our Head. So when one is in Chriſt, the Promiſes are made to him in a legal Form by reaſon of Chriſt, on whoſe Account he has
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:56657:7"/>a legal Right and Title to them, tho abſtractly conſidered none at all. Thus we may ſee there are Motives ſufficient to drive from Sinfulneſs, or draw to Holineſs, without the Doctrine of Merit, or Legal Conditions; therefore we are to keep that fundamental Doctrine at the Bottom of our Hearts, whenever we go about comparing our Works with the Reward we expect; as we find <hi>Caleb</hi> did, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 14. he begins to plead for <hi>Hebron,</hi> as if it were on Merit, <hi>I ſpied out the Land, I brought word again as it was in my Heart, I followed the Lord fully;</hi> but bottoms that on <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Oath, and that Oath on the Lord's ſpeaking that Word to <hi>Moſes:</hi> but Foundations lie deep, and are not diſcover'd on all Occaſions. <hi>If the Lord will,</hi> lies latent in the Thoughts of every Believer in all his Enterprizes, yet one would not lightly and cuſtomarily expreſs it, leſt it turn into a form of prophaning that Sacred Name, and Sacred Aſſiſtance, except on ſolemn Occaſions, when the Mind at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends it with adoring Thoughts; as <hi>David,</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29. when he and his Princes had offered for the Temple 13005000 lb. of Gold, and 2537530 lb. of Silver, they offered it willingly, but with ſolemn Acknowledgments that both it, and the Heart and Willingneſs to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it, was of God, and humble themſelves under the ſenſe of ſo great a Mercy as that Temper of Mind. I have only theſe two things to make Application of in this Affair: 1ſt, That the Woman was very ſound in this Faith: 2ly, That ſhe was very holy in her Life.</p>
            <p>The 3d Head is the Temper of <hi>Caleb</hi>'s Mind, which is only deſcribed from its Diverſity, and being alien from the Spirit of the Day; not only another from the Canaanites or Egyptians, but another from the Iſraelites. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. it's the Character of one yet in the Gall of Bitterneſs, and under the Power of Satan, that <hi>he follows the Courſe of the World:</hi> he was none of that Spirit and Temper, his was contrary, and oppoſite to the Courſe of the World: they were blind and ignorant, he of great Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacity and Judgment: they Unbelievers, Tempters, Provokers, and Rebels; he a Believer, and an obedient one: they were proud, carnal, ſelfiſh; he not.</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. A Spirit of Diſcerning, a Spirit of Judgment and ſound Mind was with him: indeed there was little Opportunity for diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering this, until the Wars and Wilderneſs were at an End; yet his Judgment and Reaſon (the grand Foundations of Learning)
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:56657:8"/>outſhin'd no leſs than 603550 Perſons, and all the Spies ſelected for Wiſdom and Diſcretion: but afterwards he and his moſt illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ſhine as the grand Patriots of Learning in the World. <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contathon</hi> the Phenician, about the Time of Judg <hi>Gideon,</hi> is rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon'd the moſt antient of Human Writers. <hi>Philo Byblius,</hi> who liv'd in <hi>Adrian</hi>'s Time, about the time of concluding the New-Teſtament-Canon, turn'd it into Greek: this Man liv'd 5 or 6 Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations after <hi>Caleb. Beroſus</hi> is another fam'd Author for Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity in the Chaldean Story, yet liv'd not before <hi>Ptolomy Philadelphus</hi> in the time of the Grecian Monarchy. At the ſame time <hi>Manetho</hi> an <hi>Egyptian</hi> flouriſh'd, who is epitomiz'd by <hi>Africanus,</hi> that liv'd about 200 Years after Chriſt. We have nothing but Fragments of the former in <hi>Joſephus</hi> and <hi>Euſebius. Annius Viterbienſis</hi> about the time of the Reformation, wrote 27 Books of Antiquity, and pretends (but without Credit) to give Compendiums of theſe Authors. But <hi>Caleb</hi> is more antient than they, or <hi>Thales</hi> the Philoſopher, or <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> the Poet in the time of King <hi>Jotham.</hi> The Pillars of <hi>Seth,</hi> from whence it's ſaid theſe Men deriv'd their greateſt Antiquities, ſtood within this Man's Mannors. <hi>Debir</hi> was the City of Pagan Learning, the moſt antient Treaſure of their Hieroglyphicks, and the Myſteries of their Religion were treaſur'd up there. <hi>Caleb</hi> gave <hi>Ptolomy</hi> (who got the Old Teſtament to be firſt turn'd into Greek, and ſanctified his great Library with that Oracle) a Pattern, for he turned <hi>Kirjath Sepher,</hi> the City of the Book, into <hi>Debir,</hi> the Sacred Word, or Oracle, from a Copy of the Law he kept there, as may appear from the Scribes of <hi>Jabez,</hi> a very near Branch of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leb,</hi> and the firſt we find of that Office, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 2.55. &amp; 4.10. he was the Inventer of it, and on that Account more honourable than his Brethren, and left us a Form of Prayer, a Monument of his Devotion, <hi>O that thou wouldſt bleſs me indeed, that thou wouldſt keep me from Evil, that it may not grieve me;</hi> at once a Pattern of Piety, and Propagater of Writing next to <hi>Moſes,</hi> who received the Art with the Law from God. The Work of a Scribe was to copy out holy Scripture from the Originals; tho ſince printing a Bible is an eaſy Purchaſe, yet 400 Years after Chriſt, a Bible was a Gift not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of an Emperor; and 100 Years before Chriſt, <hi>Ptolomy</hi> of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi> was the only King had one in his Power. And yet above 1000 Years before that <hi>Caleb</hi> has got one in his City, and has there ſet up a School of Scribes for propagating Copies of it through the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:56657:8"/>Land of <hi>Iſrael</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 2.55. The Scribes of <hi>Jabez</hi> are by ſome counted Levites, and by others <hi>Kenit, Proſelites,</hi> but againſt the Letter of the Text, which ſays they were Sons of <hi>Salma,</hi> the Son of <hi>Caleb</hi> junior, Grandchild to <hi>Caleb</hi> the Great. From which I obſerve, firſt, that tho their Critical Office began with <hi>Ezra,</hi> yet as Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribers and Copiers, they began with <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Caleb.</hi> 2ly. According to Saili in the Art, not only <hi>Egypt</hi> (as <hi>F. Simon</hi> ſays) but <hi>Babylon (Eſth.</hi> 3.) and every other State had them, yet none like <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who receiv'd the Art in a more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent manner with the Law; <hi>Euſeb. Nierem.</hi> 3ly. That (againſt <hi>F. Simon</hi> and others ſubtily enervating the Prophetical Authority of the Scriptures) <hi>Scribe</hi> and <hi>Prophet</hi> are not to be confounded; there is no Man a Prophet but by Accommodation (as <hi>Ambr.</hi> or <hi>Hilar. An.</hi> 380. in <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11. <hi>Interpretes nunc Prophetae dicuntur;</hi> Tertul. <hi>Theſaurus ſacer Corban, eleemoſynae ſacrificium, menſa altare, paſtor Sacerdos, vet Archiſynagogus, diaconus Levita)</hi> except Perſons inſpired of God, <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.22. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.20. <hi>vide</hi> Dr. Pocock <hi>de porta Moſis.</hi> 4ly. The Notion of ſecondary Prophets, <hi>viz.</hi> Interpreters by acquired Skill, is of ſmall Probability, and of moſt dangerous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.27. &amp; 13.1. &amp; 15.32. &amp; 19.6. &amp; 21.9. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. &amp; 14. <hi>Juſt. Mart.</hi> Ap. 2dâ, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Clem. Alex. Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 11. in the Epiſt. to the Corinth. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of Prophetick Gifts, for he knew they had that Gift. <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28. he that <hi>propheſies, ſpeaks all from the Spirit,</hi> &amp;c. the Subjection of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits to the Prophets was to try if of God or not, if a real Inſpiration or falſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence. <hi>Vide Anton. Van Dale;</hi> If we admit of Prophets by Pains and ordinary Gifts, we indanger that infallible Foundation of Prophets, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.20. on which we are built, and which is more ſure than any Human Teſtimony, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.36, 39. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19.</note>, and together with it in <hi>Hebron</hi> a more antient City than the moſt antient <hi>Zoan</hi> or <hi>Tanais</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> whither the Old Philoſophers travelled to gather the Traditions and Dictates of the Antients. Heaps of the greateſt Antiquities in the World were to be found in <hi>Hebron;</hi> ſo that in this he ſeems preferable to <hi>Moſes,</hi> who was inſtructed in all the Learning of <hi>Egypt;</hi> for he was inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in all the Learning of <hi>Hebron</hi> or <hi>Kirjath-arba,</hi> where the Pillars of <hi>Seth</hi> ſtood, on which the Hiſtory of Affairs before the Flood were wrote, <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve, Abraham</hi> and <hi>Sarab</hi> buried, from thence called <hi>Kirjath-arba,</hi> or the City of the 4 famous Perſons. Altho there is as much Diſparity between the Lines of my propoſed Parallels, as between the Years of Life in that Age and this; yet if we throw in the Advantage of Goſpel-Light, there was not a Scribe at <hi>Jabez,</hi> that knew more, or as much as She; tho <hi>Joſeph</hi> was called a <hi>Zophna Paaneah,</hi> an Inſpecter into the hid things of God, and <hi>Daniel,</hi> a <hi>Belteſhazzar,</hi> one who had the Treaſures of <hi>Bell</hi> reveal'd to him: for <hi>we with open Face, behold as in a Glaſs</hi> greater things than they. What <hi>Daniel</hi> obtain'd by Prayer and Supplication, with Faſting,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:56657:9"/>Sackcloth and Aſhes, as one greatly beloved, to wit, a crucified Chriſt, an everlaſting Righteouſneſs brought in by him, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. and what Diſcovery he obtain'd of the Churches Viciſſitudes, and the World's Revolutions until the ſtanding up of <hi>Michael</hi> the Prince, we have all in clear Hiſtory, excepting 2 Turns that begin almoſt to look upon us thro' the Diſpenſations of Providence: and in both of theſe I may ſafely affirm, that ſhe had Knowledg beyond the common Attainments of her Sex; and I have often thought it was through the defect of her Library, that her Judgment and Sagacity did not render her very conſpicuous in the World. This Knowledg is ſo neceſſary a Step to all Goodneſs, that it's both Sin and Shame, a preſent Loſs, and Danger of eternal, not to imitate, or endeavour to outrun her in it: for a Man may have a kind of Knowledg without being good or gracious; but without Knowledg the Scripture aſſerts the Heart is not Good. A blind Eye is as good as an ignorant Spirit; it is this kind of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs makes up a ſpiritual Hell. The Lord ſays, <hi>his People were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed for lack of Knowledg:</hi> and as a Soul cannot be good, ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can it do good; we cannot worſhip God: the Athenian Worſhip of an unknown God, and a blind Sacrifice, are both alike unacceptable to him. What a Nullity does Chriſt put upon the Samaritan Worſhip, when he told them, they <hi>worſhipt they knew not what?</hi> And as it cannot do good, it cannot receive Good. Faith is the Soul's Hand; but a Hand without the Conduct of an Eye, may lay hold on that which never will ſupport it. It's by Knowledg many are juſtified; it's by Knowledg eternal Life is begun. It is neceſſary in our Days, if we would be able to defend the Truth, or withſtand the Gainſayers, to be not only acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Fundamentals of Religion, and the way of a Sinner's Salvation, but to extend our Pains to the uttermoſt Compaſs of things contained within Sacred Writ: for ſurely what God thought fit to reveal, and record in a peculiar manner for our uſe, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes us to ſtudy: we cannot count it miſpent time to learn, when Omniſcience condeſcends to be Teacher. But beſides, there is this peculiar Reaſon for it, becauſe the Deiſts, and they who deny the Divinity of the Scriptures, derogate ſo far from them, as to leave uncertain what's Divine, what not; of this kind are <hi>Eben Eſra, Hobs, Spinoſa,</hi> Father <hi>Simon,</hi> the Author of the <hi>Five Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> &amp;c. for the Grounds of their Unbelief are generally built
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:56657:9"/>upon the Circumſtances in
<note n="*" place="bottom">F. <hi>Simon</hi> finds three Authors to the five Books of <hi>Moſes;</hi> 1. Himſelf, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the Law and Ceremonies. 2. The Publick Scribes, Authors of the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. 3. Of many Additions, which he falſly concludes to be ſince added or altered, the later Scribes, who compendized the publick Records. From whence he concludes; we know not what is his, what not. Or, as <hi>Du Verſe</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides the Scripture; 1. Some Divine, <hi>i. e.</hi> where it ſays ſo. 2. Some Humane. 3. Some Prophane, as <hi>David</hi>'s Curſes.</note> Scripture leaſt minded by Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors or Interpreters, as being of little Moment, ſome apparent Contradictions in Time, Place, Genealogies, or Titles; for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.6. <hi>And the Canaanite was then in the Land:</hi> hence would they infer that <hi>Moſes</hi> was not the Author of all wrote in theſe Books that bear his Name, and what is ſuperadded by we know not whom, is not to be received as infallible. But there is no Foundation in the Text for their Concluſion; for what Abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity is it for <hi>Moſes</hi> to tell us the Canaanite was in the Land, when <hi>Abraham</hi> paſſed through it? neither is Reaſon wanting for it, <hi>viz.</hi> to give account of God's Fidelity to him in protecting of him when he paſſed even through it to take Seizin of it, though the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naanite was there, whom he came to diſinherit.</p>
            <p>A 2d Ingredient in this ſingular Temper of Mind was Faith, ver. 11. <hi>How long will it be ere they believe?</hi> Heb. 3.18. <hi>To whom ſware he, that they ſhould not enter into his Reſt, but to them that believed not? But</hi> Caleb <hi>was not of that Spirit.</hi> V. 9. <hi>Their Defence is departed from them, and the Lord is with us; fear them not.</hi> Heb. 3.16. <hi>Howbeit not all that came out of</hi> Egypt <hi>by</hi> Moſes <hi>did provoke and disbelieve.</hi> And <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.3. <hi>They which believed did enter into Reſt.</hi> He could not follow the Lord fully without Faith, nor was his Courage againſt ſo powerful an Enemy founded on any other Bottom: by human Eyes they were like a <hi>David</hi> before <hi>Goliah;</hi> nay in their own Eſteem, and in the Eſteem of the <hi>Anakims</hi> their Enemies, they were like Graſhopers, <hi>Chap.</hi> 13.33. But by the Eye of Faith he ſaw God as a ſufficient Confederate and Aſſiſtant againſt all the Strength of <hi>Canaan;</hi> the <hi>Anakims</hi> were like Graſhopers in compariſon of God, and the meaneſt Worm he aſſiſts. <hi>Caleb's</hi> Knowledg was qualified or ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified by Faith: It is a common Axiom, that Knowledg may be without Faith, but not Faith without Knowledg; they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated as a living Creature and a rational Creature; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e may live without Reaſon, but not exert Reaſon without Life. This was
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:56657:10"/>a Grace in my Parallel, not only well rooted, but well fruited; the Service ſhe delighted in, could only receive its Reward in the other Life. Jeſus Chriſt was at once the Object of her Love and Truſt; her Lot, with the moſt of Believers, had its wilderſome Circumſtances, and through it ſhe travelled, <hi>leaning on her Beloved.</hi> The ſacred Oracles, which are the Directors and Grounds of Faith, were the Objects of her daily Study. Peace with God, as the Mediator's Purchaſe, was the great Expectation of her Hope, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the ſeeing King <hi>Solomon,</hi> with the Crown upon his Head, glorified in his Saints, and admired of all that believe: through whom her Faith was finally and ultimately termina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on God as a faithful Creator, from whom originally all Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs flowed on the Head and Members of the Church, which ſhe longed to ſee preſented without Spot or Wrinkle. This is what of neceſſity we muſt imitate our <hi>Caleb</hi> in; without Faith there is no pleaſing of God: they that believe not, are condemned al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.1. not only this, but all the Elders from <hi>Abel</hi> are propoſed as the Cloud in the Wilderneſs to follow; nor is <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> to be excluded from being Drops of that dewy Cloud; for though on Marriage he called his Wife <hi>Iſhah,</hi> of Man, or Woeman, yet after the Promiſe of the Redeeming Seed of the Woman, he calls her <hi>Eve,</hi> the Mother of him that quickens or enlivens all; and the like Faith ſhe profeſſes and writes on her el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Son <hi>Cain, I have gotten</hi> that Seed, <hi>the Man the Lord,</hi> I have born <hi>Immanuel,</hi> Gen. 4.1. as the moſt Critical do interpret the Words. The only Exception about this univerſal Neceſſity, at leaſt among whom I have now to do, is Infants; it is ſuppoſed many of them are ſaved, but queſtioned if Faith have any Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentality in their Salvation, ſince Faith ſuppoſes Knowledg: nay the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. ſays, it <hi>comes by Hearing,</hi> which ſuppoſes not only the Exerciſe of a Spirit, but of bodily Organs. I ſhall ſay the more to it, having juſt now received a Letter about it, and two days ago another, beſide Viſits. I do profeſs it to be my O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, but not a neceſſary Foundation, no not to any Doctrine I then propoſed; for Charity for their Salvation through the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Chriſt, which the Letter grants, is ſufficient for all the Intents I mentioned it for: however I ſhall ſhew my Opinion is neither ſingular, nor wants Probability. As to the firſt, it's the common Opinion of the Papiſts, as we may ſee from <hi>Bellarmine</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:56657:10"/>and <hi>Gregorius de Valentia</hi> on Baptiſm; ſo <hi>Suarez</hi> on <hi>Thomas;</hi> and the <hi>Conference</hi> at <hi>Ratisbon,</hi> they deny that Infants have actual Faith, but grant habitual, which is ſufficient for my Intent: but if we go to the Lutheran Churches, they univerſally aſcribe an actual Faith to Infants; their Arguments are, that the Spirit of God which aſſerts that they that have not Faith are in a State of Condemnation, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16. <hi>John</hi> 3.18. does aſſert that little ones have Faith, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.6. <hi>Whoſo ſhall offend one of thoſe little ones that believe on me;</hi> the like in <hi>Mark</hi> 9.42. <hi>Ver.</hi> 36. we find that it was ſuch a Child that Chriſt took in his Arms, ſuch an one that has Angels for its Guardians, ſuch an one as the Scripture calls <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.15. ſuch as were brought to Chriſt in the Arms of others, not on their own Feet; the Bringers whereof the Diſciples rebuk'd, not themſelves, being uncapable of Converſe: Jeſus ſays, the Kingdom of God conſiſts of ſuch. And if there were no actual Sin in them, I ſhould be apt to have Charity for all of them: for the <hi>much more</hi> on the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi>'s Side will ſcarce ſuffer any to be condemned where that is alone, without the leaſt Fruit or Effect. The greateſt Objection lying againſt theſe Texts is, that the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants ſpoken of, ſeem to be capable of Offence: to which, if we take the Interpretation of <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> with other Fathers, for an anſwer; to <hi>offend</hi> here is not barely to give an evil Example, but to reject, which was a Fault Chriſt reproves his Diſciples for: the Interpretation is the more receptible, becauſe Offending and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving are put in oppoſition to one another. The common O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of Calviniſts is, that they have the Seeds of Faith, or ſome Gift like Faith, or a certain Inclination to Faith: ſo that there is ſcarce any Party left but Socinians to join with in deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Infants to have any Faith
<note n="*" place="bottom">Indeed Mr. <hi>Lock</hi> denies Ideas innate, but determines not how early they may be conveyed by Senſes, neither does he ever pretend to bar Heaven's. Influence from creating Ideas in a Soul where its Caſe is not a ſpan long, nor its bodily Tools fit for Work.</note>. Indeed <hi>Socinus</hi> ſays about the State of <hi>Adam,</hi> that it's ridiculous to attribute Faith in God to Infants, and is like to the Dream of a feveriſh Man: but I cannot dream of any particular Perſons intereſted in the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt without an Union to Chriſt; and how one can be in Chriſt without Faith, or the Spirit which works Faith, is more than I can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:56657:11"/>of, or than the Scripture informs me of, which as generally attributes the Applicatory Work of Grace to the Spirit as the Redemptory to the Son. (2) I find ſome ſanctified from the Womb, and even that ſanctifying Grace in ſuch Exerciſe, as to move the very Organs of an Embryo in the Womb. Luke 1.44. <hi>The Babe leaped in my Womb for Joy.</hi> Jer. 1.5. <hi>Before thou cameſt out of the Womb, I ſanctified thee.</hi> How Sanctification can be without Faith is inconceivable, that being it the Heart is purified by, that the Soul lives by, that we are clothed with Righteouſneſs by: there can no Aſſertion be more without Exception than that <hi>John</hi> 3.5. <hi>Except a Man be born of Water and of the Spirit, he cannot enter into the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> Fleſh and Blood cannot enter there; and <hi>whatſoever is born of the Fleſh is Fleſh:</hi> ſo that one muſt be born of the Spirit before he can enter thither. But 'tis obſervable, that <hi>the Spirit blows where he liſteth;</hi> neither the Indiſpoſition of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, nor the Corruption of the Soul can impede his Creative Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: and it ſeems to me very unreaſonable to deny a Spirit's Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with the Father of Spirits, without a Capacity of conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with Man: in order to the one, the Soul muſt learn how the Glaſs of the Senſes repreſents ſuch Objects to it; nay there is need of Learning and Obſervation to know the right Hand from the Left, it's a Relation few of 40 Years underſtand: a Hand is a neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Organ to the Body, but a very foreign extrinſical thing to the Soul. If we come from Scripture to Experience and Obſervation, we find it eſſential and neceſſary to the Soul to think; it's as natural for a Spirit to think, as for a Body to be long, broad, and thick. 2ly. Wherever Thoughts are, they are good or bad: Gen. 6. <hi>The Imagination of the Thoughts of their Heart are evil continually: All that proceeds from a Spirit, is moral.</hi> Chriſt ſays, <hi>that defiles not a Man which goes in at his Mouth, but what comes out of his</hi> Heart. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. As the Father of Spirits is a quickning Spirit, the Soul is a living Spirit, the Image of him who is a pure Act. How can it live without Thought? (our Body cannot without Motion) or be ſanctified without good Thoughts? If that ſleep, what can awake it? 3ly. We find it was a common Opinion in Chriſt's Time, that an Infant was capable of ſinning before it was born, which he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thought worthy Refutation or Denial; <hi>Did this Man ſin, or his Parents, that he was born blind?</hi> If being born blind, was the Puniſhment of foregoing Sin, then the Infant could act Sin; why
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:56657:11"/>not Faith too? 4ly. Can they inform us of the Difference between a Soul newly formed by the Hand of God, and after ten or twenty Years of Age, that a Creative Operation of God ſhould be need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to work Faith in the one, but not able enough to create it in the other? One ſhould not make Exceptions to the Scriptures ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Aſſertions, without ſome clear and ſolid Reaſon; this the Socinians grant. His common way of ſaving is by Faith, and common way of working Faith is by Creation; and what Impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can reſiſt or render the Subject uncapable of that Influence? Original Sin is more powerful by Habits radicated in the Adult than in Infants; the part of this now under Conſideration is the Want of that <hi>moſt like</hi> Image of God (the Senſe of Likeneſs and Image, an Hebraiſm;) God cures that Privation by planting it in the Soul: the Scripture informs us it conſiſts <hi>in Knowledg, Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and Holineſs.</hi> Are the Infants ſanctified without being transformed into the Likeneſs of God? that is a Contradiction; and it is as great a one to imagine the Image of God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Knowledg. Pſal. 8.3. <hi>Out of the Mouths of Babes and Suck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings thou haſt ordained Praiſe.</hi> This is not objectively only, as the Heavens declare God's Glory, but actively with their Mouths; which (<hi>Mat.</hi> 21.15.) was fulfilled by the little Children that went with their Mothers to the Temple: though (<hi>Luke</hi> 18.) the Diſciples began (it's like) the Hoſannas, yet even Sucklings of two or three Years old filled up the Chorus: And could their Tongues praiſe him, and not their Souls think of him? I cannot imagine, that the Difference between a Suckling's Soul and a new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born or unborn Babe's is much. 5ly. Can all the Pains of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate Man ſtudy himſelf into a Spiritual diſcerning? 1 Cor. 2.12. <hi>The natural Man knoweth not,</hi> &amp;c. And can the want of that Pains hinder the Holy Ghoſt from induing the Soul with that holy Unction? Suppoſe the Child die, and be carried in the Arms of its Angels to Glory, will it want Knowledg there? or do the unprepared Organs, while in the Body, prevent the Holy Spirit's Influence? 6ly. Take the Experiment of a pregnant long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Woman, and we may find Willings and Nillings, Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations and Averſions as powerful in an Infant unborn, as in the moſt adult Age. Is the Soul already able by its Maker's ordinary Influence to reach, and govern the Imagination of Child and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:56657:12"/>both ſo early
<note n="*" place="bottom">If from the Mother, the Creator's Influence is more ſtill; but that the Longing is from the Child, not the Mother, we may conclude, firſt from this, there are not ſuch powerful Appetites in her when not pregnant. 2ly. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe immediately bringing forth by it, the Mother longs no more, the Child continues to crave, refuſes all things elſe, moſt greedily eats that, (tho Food that needs a moſt ſtrong digeſtive Diſpoſition) and is eaſy and ſatisfied with it.</note>, and his regenerating Influence not create as powerful ſpiritual Inclinations towards himſelf? May not the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject be as particularly diſtinguiſh'd and determin'd, and as cloſely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in Spirituals? and ſhall not that be called Faith? 7ly. It is a common Dictate, that many Probabilities make a Demonſtration, or ſure Argument; and I ſhall give as many more when theſe are anſwer'd: but I am afraid I have given too many for ſuch an end.</p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude with <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.11. from which I make theſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks: 1. He denies not thinking, but doing. 2. He denies not that Infants may do Good or Evil in the Womb, for he makes two Negations, <hi>neither.</hi> 3. He aſſerts that God had both elected and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the one; 1ſt, Before Birth: 2ly, Yet more early, before doing Good or Evil (ſays <hi>Jac. Alt.</hi>) before the ſtrugling in the Womb, <hi>Gen.</hi> 25. God having called the one in the Womb. The Enmity between the two Seeds made <hi>Rebecca</hi>'s Belly the Stage of the begun War; the Lord tells her, there were two manner of People in her Womb; this Text tells us that God's Calling made the Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<note n="†" place="bottom">For, <hi>viz. The Elder ſhall ſerve the Younger,</hi> is by <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>ver.</hi> 13. to ariſe from God's Love, and <hi>ver.</hi> 11. to break forth firſt in Calling. Or the 11th <hi>ver.</hi> is the Senſe of two Scriptures, <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.23. and <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.2. Love is explain'd by Purpoſe, and Maſtery explain'd by Calling. The Spirit of God in <hi>Hoſea</hi> 12.3. applies as little a Story as this Strugling to the Spirit of God as Author, <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.26. his <hi>Hand took hold on Eſau</hi>'s <hi>Heel. Hoſea</hi> from this moſt ſharply reproves <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Poſterity as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generating from their Father; You (ſays he) confederate with the Aſſyrians, and carry Oil to <hi>Egypt</hi> for aſſiſtance, but <hi>Jacob took his Brother by the Heel in the Womb;</hi> how entirely did he depend on God's Aſſiſtance, how early did he long for the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, how highly did he eſteem the Promiſes? And he adds another Inſtance of the ſame, <hi>ver.</hi> 4. from <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.24. from which we may further conclude, if his Victory over the Angel was by Faith, ſo was his Wreſtling with <hi>Eſau</hi> in Faith. <hi>Joh. Schmidt</hi> draws this Doctrine from it, Infants are capable of the Spirit's Illumination and Operations; for by this Grace he wreſtled with <hi>Eſau.</hi>
               </note>. Faith is always eſteem'd the immediate Effect of Calling. Now here were Works and War in the Womb: Works and Victory are through Faith, <hi>for the Children being not yet born, neither having done Good or Evil, that the Purpoſe of God according to Election might ſtand, not of Works, but of him that calleth.</hi> I have treated this as an Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:56657:12"/>all along for Faith as it is God's Gift; the Father's drawing to the Son, by perſwading and alluring, and the Son's apprehending the Soul immediately, is all that I think neceſſary to plead for, ſince Faith juſtifies as it unites to Chriſt; and I am ſure if the Father's drawing, and the Son's apprehending unite not our coming, our believing which is the Fruit of it, will not: his Calling unites as much as our anſwering; and the Denial of this in Infants ſeems ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtrange: it is ſafe enough to aſſert Salvation in ſome without Means, or under other Means than we enjoy; but to aſſert Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion without Grace, either redeeming Grace in the Son, or apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Grace in the Spirit, is trampling on Chriſt's Blood, and doing deſpite to the Spirit, ſetting up another Goſpel; and to think the Spirit works different Effects in different Souls, is as abſurd: there is one Faith, as there is one Spirit; what are contrary to the Effects of the Spirit in the Goſpel are Fruits of the Fleſh, and Faith is the firſt Fruit of the Spirit: or to think that the Spirit of God is in a Soul, dwells there, works there without Effects, is as ſtrange. I have always, as <hi>Hen. Alt.</hi> put this among my Problems, <hi>i. e.</hi> abſtruſe Queſtions, yet do think it of greater moment, than that about In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-Baptiſm; for the one is about the manner of a Goſpel-Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, the great Virtue whereof lies in doing it with a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, there is nothing in the Ceremony of moment, abſtractly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered: the other is about Goſpel-Grace; if one kind of Grace for the Old, another for the Young; one kind for the Dumb, Deaf, Diſtracted, and who had no Opportunity of exerciſing their Senſes about external Means of Grace, another for them who have; if God, who has not limited Means by Grace, has limited Grace by Means; if the Spirit cannot ſanctify my Soul, and fill it with Faith, Love and Patience, becauſe when an Infant I loſt my hearing; if one Man can be juſtified by another's Faith, <hi>viz.</hi> the Parents, or Chriſt's, as <hi>Antin.</hi> ſay, as well as another's Righteouſneſs, <hi>viz.</hi> his; 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 14. there was ſome good thing, a real, ſpiritual, acceptable Good in <hi>Jeroboam</hi>'s young Child; there is little reaſon to think it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey'd by means of Grace, the Education of a Pagan Idolatrous Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily did not afford it, tho under ſome Places of Popery it may; the Child may be was not yet capable of any.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall return to the Adult. If Faith be neceſſary in Infants, ſurely it's neceſſary in the Adult: if without Hope, we are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God; if without Faith, we are without Chriſt, the Word
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:56657:13"/>preach'd has never profited us, the Goſpel is in vain, and its Grace too to us, if not mix'd with Faith: but where it is, all things are chang'd from a State of Death to Life, the Soul lives by Faith; it's worſe than a dead ſtinking Carcaſe, until Faith dawn in it. 2ly. It brings Light into the Soul, that was like a Dungeon before; it is the Evidence of things not ſeen. 3ly. It's an humbling Grace, for by it the Soul is convinc'd of its Sin and Guilt: a Man will never own that he was conceiv'd in Sin, born in Iniquity, by nature a Child of Wrath, until the Light of Faith ſhine; that will make the Soul ſay with <hi>Job, I have heard of thee by the hearing of the Ear, but now having ſeen thee, I abhor my ſelf in Duſt and Aſhes.</hi> 4ly. By Faith the Soul glorifies God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.20. as <hi>Abraham</hi> did, it will honour him in his Precepts, Promiſes, Providences; it will bring every Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, every Thought and carnal Reaſoning into ſubjection to Chriſt. 5ly. By it the Soul is preſerv'd in danger, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5. it's the Soul's Shield of Defence, and Sword of Defiance. 6ly. By this we have Acceſs to God, and approach the Throne of Grace with Boldneſs. 7ly. By this we are patient in Tribulation; we can ſuffer Reproaches, while we truſt in the Living God, and have hop'd-for things realiz'd and preſented to the Soul. 8ly. It's a Rarity, and yet a very ſeaſonable Grace. <hi>Egypt</hi> was a Type of Popery, and the Wilderneſs a Type of the Brinks of the Church's Deliverance: Faith was then rare, but 2 of 700000 entred <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan</hi> for want of it, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. So Chriſt ſays, <hi>When he comes, ſcarce ſhall Faith be found upon the Earth.</hi> Would we know the Reaſon of our turning thus into the Wilderneſs again, when we thought we were on Mount <hi>Piſga?</hi> we want Faith. It's the very time for the Faith and Patience of the Saints, and they want it; like the fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Virgins, ſome want Oil, all are aſleep when the Bridegroom calls. 9ly. As it's rare, it's difficult: it's as eaſy for God to produce it in the youngeſt Infant as in the oldeſt Man; it's a Fruit of the Spirit of God, not of our Spirits: all things in Man are againſt it, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for it; the ſtronger his carnal Reaſonings grow, the more difficult is the Work of Faith: The Philoſophers were the Goſpel's greateſt Enemies. To ſuppoſe it in <hi>Adam</hi> before the Fall, had been to ſuppoſe what was repugnant to, and would have over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown his State. Fallen Man needs the Spirit to convince him that he is in Unbelief, needs Chriſt being given for him, needs a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing given and drawn to Chriſt by the Powerful Arm of the Lord.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:56657:13"/>Let not us be among the common ſort of Iſraelites, <hi>that deſpiſed the pleaſant Land, and believed not his Word,</hi> Pſal. 106.24. who could not enter in becauſe of Unbelief, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. laſt. <hi>Zachariah,</hi> who walk'd in all the Ordinances blameleſs, was ſtruck dumb 9 Months for an Act of Unbelief, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.20. Chriſt upbraids his Diſciples for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in another Act, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.14. We have great and precious Promiſes of a better <hi>Canaan,</hi> a more glorious Theocracy; let us ſtrive to enter by Faith. The Emperor's Victory over the Turks, his planting his Ephodical Tent between the Seas in the glorious Land, would open a <hi>Piſga</hi> Sight of it to us, <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.45. Shall not we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve God's Word? or can we deny his giving of it? His Word, his Promiſe, his Covenant, his Oath we have, his Seal we have, the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of our Fathers we have. Was not God always faithful?</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>But we cannot believe of our ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1ſt. We can forbear many things which may hinder the Exerciſe of it, as a Woman may prevent Miſcarriage. 2ly. We can be humbled for groſs Sins, and let Convictions take place. 3ly. We can uſe Means, and be diligent in the practice of all Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances. 4ly. We can be watchful in the uſe of them, waiting with Fear and Trembling, if the Angel will move in theſe Waters. 5ly. We can try it, endeavour, go about it, ſeek out the Promiſes, meditate on them, propoſe them. 6ly. We can do this in ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to God, waiting if he will bleſs the Loaves in the eating. 7ly. Exerciſe Acts of Self-renouncing in the Performances, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.16. even the very Act it ſelf: <hi>That we might be juſtified not by the Works of the Law, but by the Faith of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. A great Eſteem of Divine Bleſſings and Favours: <hi>They deſpis'd the pleaſant Land,</hi> Pſal. 106.24. <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.7. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.8. This <hi>Caleb</hi> did not, he greatly eſteem'd the Land: there is yet a better Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try and City (<hi>Heb.</hi> 11.) in our Promiſes. My Parallel was a great Admirer of this New <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and no unthankful Undervaluer of our Day of ſmall things; ſhe was not of his Temper, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd a part of <hi>Paris</hi> to a Portion in Paradiſe. All come ſhort of this Pattern, who love <hi>Egypt. If any Man love the World, the Love of God is not in him.</hi> 2. If any are lazy, and ſtrive not to enter by the ſtrait Gate into this Reſt. 3. When Heaven is not counted worthy the Dangers and Difficulties we incur by the way, when the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kims</hi> conquer our Faith. Let us think on ſinging the Song of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and the Lamb, of the 5th Kingdom in Succeſſion.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:56657:14"/>4. A Publick Spirit: Her Pains were not ſo much for building her own Family as the Church of God; a great and pious Zeal of this kind was like the Sacred Fire on the Altar that never went out: I may ſay, ſhe went about continually doing good; to the Rich, minding them of their Duty with that Prudence, that I never heard her complain'd of as a buſy Body or the like; to the Poor, relieving them: the Decay of this is of a mighty threatning Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect. Many counted Patriots of their Countrey, have diſcovered Self too much, a powerful End and Principle, and the Effect of it is among the Body of the People; they think there is no ſuch thing as <hi>Tribuni Plebis:</hi> If any Man ſeem to ſhew a Zeal for his Countrey, the Vulgar Verdict is, <hi>Does he want a Place?</hi> never was a Nation leſs liable to idolize the Princes of their Tribes, yet no doubt there are <hi>Calebs</hi> among them; without ſome remarkable Revoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, none or one is like to be our Lot. The Heat of Contention between <hi>Non</hi> and <hi>Con</hi> never did appear more abated: this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment ſeems like the Tree that ſweetned the Waters of <hi>Mara;</hi> yet where is the Man of ſo publick a Spirit, as to reform the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes both Sides complain of? One is that the Curſes of the Law ſhould ſtand in place of the Diſcipline of the Goſpel: publick Prayers are conſtantly according to form ſaid in <hi>Lent</hi> for mending this; hence is a publick Acknowledgment that the Church wants the primitive Diſcipline. 2ly. That there ſhould be no Partition between the World and Church of Chriſt, no Door of Entrance into the ſacred Society of Saints: this has made the Church the World, the vileſt and moſt abominable of Men (like the Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation that maketh deſolate) ſitting where they ought not, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faning the Lord's Table, confirming their own Damnation: it were a Seaſon to perpetuate the Honour of ſome Publick Spirit; but moſt mind their own things, few Chriſt's.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Of a Peaceable Spirit. <hi>Caleb</hi> was none of the ſeditious Rebels that were for caſting off <hi>Moſes,</hi> and making another Captain, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whom they might return to <hi>Egypt.</hi> My Parallel imitating our unerring Pattern, has often rebuk'd ſuch haſty Diſciples, that were immediately for bringing Fire from Heaven on <hi>Samaria;</hi> ſhe was no Deſpiſer of Authority, though a Longer for that fifth kind of Government, that all the Kings of the World ſhall never prevent: happy they <hi>who kiſs the Son, and put their Truſt in him.</hi> It is nigh and neceſſary: Let us follow <hi>Caleb</hi>'s Example, not a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:56657:14"/>
               <hi>Corah</hi>'s or an <hi>Abſalom</hi>'s, filling our own Place, doing our own Buſineſs, and with Faith, Prayer, and Patience wait for Chriſt's ſecond Coming.</p>
            <p n="6">6. A Spirit of Courage and Charity: he would have ventured againſt the Sons of <hi>Anak;</hi> he run the Risk of the turbulent Rabble, when nothing but God's immediate appearing could have ſaved his Life. He would fain have ſaved <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and have perſwaded them not to rebel againſt God, whatever was the Conſequence. <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhewed yet more of this Spirit, who preferr'd the ſaving of the People to the monopolizing all the Promiſes, and the whole fruitful Land for his own Family.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Of an healing uniting Spirit. If ſhe found any to be of the <hi>Houſhold of Faith,</hi> it was not in her Power to ſhut up Bowels of Compaſſion; though ſhe was ſettled in particular Fellowſhip with them whoſe Cuſtoms her own Judgment moſt harmonized with, yet ſhe was for a Bond of Peace wherever there was Union through the Cement of the Holy Spirit: ſhe was not for rejecting whom Chriſt had received, a great Rule for Communion. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.7. Though their Faith be weak, yet (<hi>Rom.</hi> 14.1.) they are to be received, and not tormented and vexed with doubtful Diſputations about Meats, or keeping Days, or ſome one particular Ordinance, as that of <hi>Circumciſion.</hi> At firſt the believing Jews rejected the Fellowſhip of the Gentiles for want of it, they unjuſtly compelled them to it: But afterwards, when the Roman Governours began to diſtinguiſh between the Jews and Chriſtians thro' <hi>Pliny</hi>'s Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that the Jews were hated of the Romans, and cut off for their cruel Murders and Slaughter, but the Chriſtians more favoured for their peaceful Tempers; ſome of the Gentile Believers, though unjuſtly too, rejected the Communion of the Jews, this was <hi>Diotrephes</hi>'s Fault, 3 <hi>John ver.</hi> 10. Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtick
<note n="*" place="bottom">Vide Ittig. de haereſ. &amp; Stockmannum.</note> Authors inform us, that his Pride in doing by himſelf what was only in the Power of the whole Church to do, was his great Sin. There is in our Day the like Fault among ſome about Infant-Baptiſm; the leſs the Difference is, the greater the Sin is in making that Difference a Partition-wall of Diviſion. The Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference is not about the total neglect of the Ordinance [though I do hear ſome are run to that Extremity] both Sides grant its Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:56657:15"/>and Uſe as an initiating Ordinance, the firſt viſible Mark of a Diſciple or Chriſtian; he that utterly omits it, is by Profeſſion a Pagan, though it may be a Believer: indeed he deals baſely by the Saviour he believes in. 2ly. The Difference is not about the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject (I confeſs ſome run to the Extremity here too, baptizing all preſented to them) <hi>viz.</hi> Believers; for if we did not think that ſome Infants had Faith, we ſhould baptize none of them: The Queſtion is then about the Objects or Grounds of Charity. Now let the Error be on which Side ſoever; the Queſtion is whether it be a ſufficient Ground of Separation, or refuſing Communion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe my Charity is more extenſive than yours. I (may be) think, ſince God has revealed it, and we ſee it fulfilled, (though not without many Exceptions of bad Children) that God's common Road and Method of bringing his Elect upon the Stage of being, is thro' the Loins and Bowels of them that are Elect and Believers, though he has not tied himſelf to it, (then indeed it would be more than a Ground of Charity) there being many Proſelytes in all A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, even out of <hi>Cham</hi>'s Line; yet this is the King's high Road: and indeed the Stop that was put to it (in cutting off this Entail among the Jews, and beginning afreſh with the Gentiles, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafting theſe formerly wild Branches to ſuck fully as much Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and Oil from the Root as the native Branches) was ſuch a Deviation from this wonted way of Divine Influence, that it has been but once in the World, will never be again, was not without repeated Prophecies to prevent ſtumbling about it; and that once was not a total Deviation from the common Road, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny being continued. 2ly. Becauſe it was for a time only: <hi>touching the Election, they are beloved for the Fathers;</hi> there is a Life and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection to come to their Dead
<note n="*" place="bottom">I deſire in this to be underſtood as obſerving the Difference between the Jewiſh Church, and God's Method of propagating Churches among the Gentiles,</note>. 3ly. They have no groſs Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, no viſible Outbreakings, no apparent Blains or Boils from the bitter Root of Original Sin; they have only againſt them what is conveyed through the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> and what ſecret Emanations from it are contained within the Compaſs and Sphere of pure Thought or Imagination. But then we have the <hi>much more</hi> of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant Grace, the <hi>much more</hi> of the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> for them. I do aſſert that this Extent of Charity in any Man, though pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:56657:15"/>and put in practice, ought not to be a Bar for which any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church ſhould refuſe him Fellowſhip and Communion.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Difference is about the Manner or Quantity of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this initiating Ceremony is to be performed with, if Dipt or Sprinkled. Let us now take a like Caſe we can think on without Prejudice, <hi>viz.</hi> the Cup in the Lord's Supper: Suppoſe then ſome ſcrutinous Mind, and ſcrupling Conſcience ſhould queſtion whether any receive the Lord's Supper, who drink not a whole Cup; it is ſaid, <hi>Drink this Cup: Is ſipping drinking? or is a Sip a Cup?</hi> Would it not be unreaſonable to refuſe a Man Communion that would on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take a Sip, when the Body of the Church were for each drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Cup? It would be of this Importance; Sir, you ſhall not be of our Church, if you take not off your Cup. Some Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy like this was between the Gentile Chriſtians and Jewiſh, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding which <hi>Paul</hi> (<hi>Eph.</hi> 4.) informs them the Baptiſm was one, <hi>One Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſm.</hi> From Mount <hi>Sinai</hi> until Chriſt's Reſurrection, that is, during the Jewiſh Church-Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Dipping was the manner; after Chriſt's Reſurrection (<hi>Mat.</hi> 28.) he gives a new Inſtitution more ſutable to the Conſtitution wherein he intended to make light Burdens and eaſy Yokes; after which we hear not of their going to the Water, but the Water coming to them, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.47. Some other differences (<hi>Acts.</hi> 19.) there were between <hi>John</hi>'s Baptiſm and Chriſt's, but that is not my Buſineſs; it is Union, Love, Peace, notwithſtanding that Difference, that is my Buſineſs, and ſhall conclude it with a Saying of a Friend and Brother, If a Seal ſhould be ſet to a Blank ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, and God afterward condeſcend to fill up the Bond, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever valid ſuch an Act might be among Men, no doubt it's good in the Sight of God.</p>
            <p>The 4th Branch is the Practice that flowed from this Temper of Mind: <hi>He followed the Lord fully,</hi> wholly, conſtantly, upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; there was a Fulneſs in what Good he did. This Fulneſs
<note n="*" place="bottom">Joſias <hi>turned unto God according to all contained in the Law.</hi> David <hi>had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect unto all God's Precepts, and refrained his Feet from every evil Way,</hi> Pſal. 119.128. <hi>I eſteem all thy Precepts concerning all things to be right. Euſtathius</hi> ſays, the Law is copulative in the Precept, Love God and thy Neighbour, but disjunctive in the Threat, Do all or die: Mat. 23.32, <hi>This ought you to have done, and not left the other undone.</hi>
               </note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:56657:16"/>the Rule of our Practice and Profeſſion; he was not for half-work, almoſt a Chriſtian, he was for all the Parts of our Duty to God and Man, a ſound Faith, a holy Life, pure Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and appointed Government. Search moſt of Profeſſors, and you will find them lame in ſome of theſe. But I muſt ſay of this good Woman, ſhe was good at this too; though ſhe was of large Charity to others, ſhe laid ſtrict Bonds on her own Neck, and was faithful to the Light God gave her. And this is a ſingular thing in our Day: many think Doctrine and Practice are to be minded, but the other two, eſpecially Church-Government, is a Matter of Indifferency; and yet it's viſibly from a Defect in that, that this Nation is ſo full of Unholineſs, the ſacred Privileges proper to Believers being thrown to worſe than Dogs, before whom ſuch Pearls are not to be caſt. I ſhall propoſe to every conſcientious Chriſtian the Method of <hi>Turetin</hi>'s defending the Reformation from Popery: <q>It pleaſed God (ſays he) to open the Eyes of ſome, who ſaw themſelves inſtead of being in a Church of Chriſt, to be in a Society that had Error in its Doctrine, Idolatry in its Worſhip, Tyranny in its Government; it was unlawful to live in that, and unlawful to live without publick Worſhip: to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Sin in either Extreme, we did confederate into Societies for publick Worſhip, and called whom God had enabled and ſent to publick and ſacred Office, for adminiſtring Ordinances and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline among us.</q> The like ſays Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> on the ſame Subject. <hi>Strauchus</hi> adds, that the Civil <hi>Comitia</hi> of <hi>Spire</hi> had no Power over them in Matters of Faith or Worſhip, and therefore the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, tho fewer in Number, acted nothing repugnant to the Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the Empire. Nor has a Synod to do with any thing but the Churches they repreſent in the Affairs that are ſacred.
<note n="*" place="bottom">The Clergy's intermedling with the National Affairs, has provoked nurſing Fathers to be cruel Step-fathers. The Church's grand Apoſtacy began together with her Inroads upon the Civil Power: and indeed where two Powers are of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual Extent, that which governs the Mind moſt, is like to command moſt; if the one promiſe Heaven, and threaten Hell, and render it credible to the ignorant; the other only promiſe Protection from a foreign Power, who will let him be Cobler ſtill if he live peaceably, and threatens only a temporal Death that ſometime ſhortly he muſt ſuffer; we may eaſily gueſs, and hundreds of Years Experience hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced who ſhall be Slave, who Governour, Pope or Emperour, King or Synod.</note> It is true, this Affair is but a Hedg, but we have a moſt doleful Proſpect of the Flock's Condition by its Removal, or never being built.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:56657:16"/>See you that deſign the Good of your own Souls or Poſterities, who value Loyalty to Chriſt as King, who would do as much as you can to reform a Nation, get into, or build up Church-Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties with Walls of Government, Doors, or Ways of Entrance to the Good, all the really Good, and thundring Exits to profane Hypocrites, when their Vileneſs diſcovers them. It is neither the Intereſt nor the Duty of a Magiſtrate to meddle in this: they ſweam on the Peoples Inclination, the Sin lies at the Door of Well-wiſhers to Reformation; the hunting out of bad Houſes is a good thing, but it will never do the 10th part of Service, tho it ſhould ſucceed, that this will. This may be my laſt Sermon too, and I leave it as my Advice; nay, the Counſel of Jeſus is rejected in the neglect of it. You have here a double Pattern, a <hi>Caleb</hi> in the old Church, in the Egyptian Wilderneſs, contending for Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Theocracy they were under; and a Parallel of exact Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiouſneſs to our Goſpel-Chriſtocracy. Civil Government is but human, in compariſon of its Divinity. The Church at firſt had her Cuſtoms, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.16. and theſe were copied from <hi>Paul</hi>'s, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17. that were uniform in every Church, and <hi>Paul</hi>'s from Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23. The Form of the one is Arbitrary, for the Good of the People: the Form of the other ſettled by him that is the Wiſdom of God, and cannot err in what Means conduce moſt to Souls Good; his is the only way of correcting abounding Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences: the Magiſtrate's Sword is the Medicine for Injuries. Let us leave Sin to God's alone immediate Government; <hi>Againſt thee, thee only have I ſinned</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">The Popiſh Abuſe of pretending to pardon aroſe from the primitive Practice of abſolving from Offences, the Church thereby ſignifying her Satisfaction; but it's Blaſphemy for Man to pretend the other, and Folly for the Sinner to multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply Offences by Confeſſion, when he only violates God's Law, and offends his Holy Eye.</note>. Let us be like <hi>Zachariahs</hi> and <hi>Elizabeths,</hi> walking in all the Ordinances of God blameleſly; this is our Lord Jeſus Chriſt's great Ordinance, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. at large. If I be off of my Subject, I am in in my Duty, as is every one that loves our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. And though the Perſon I ſpeak of was a Woman, I may ſay I know not whether her Skill, her Zeal or Conſcience did moſt outſhine in this very thing. And when I again conſider, I ſtand amaz'd to ſee Men of grey Hairs, good Men, ſerious
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:56657:17"/>Men, that excepting hearing a Sermon, or going to Prayer, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver make Conſcience of any other Ordinance, as if the reſt had been appointed by ſome other Authority; they pray, and cry for the Seal of the Spirit, but will want it before they ſubject to a ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ordinance: they are griev'd for abounding Scandals; while their Slight and Contempt of Ordinances is as influencive an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence as Whoring or Drinking. Surely, ſays a young Convert, there is little Religion, or Acceptableneſs with God in ſuch Duties, elſe ſuch and ſuch a good Man would not contemn them ſo. Such Profeſſors in neighbouring Nations would be counted Atheiſts, however we eſteem them here. He that dare to pick and chooſe, may on the ſame bottom throw off all. My Judgment leaves a great Bulk of the Nation's Profanity at ſuch Mens Doors, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they think of it.</p>
            <p n="2">2ly. A fulneſs in following the Lord comprehends true Principles and Ends in our Profeſſion and Practice. <hi>Iſrael</hi> was an empty Vine, bringing forth Fruit to her ſelf. A ſelfiſh End makes an empty Action. This is chiefly to be regarded in our Profeſſion, for a Man's own Soul is not edified by that; it's to glorify God in the Edification of others. A good Man is ſatisfied from within him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. A Soul is ſtrengthned, increas'd in Knowledg, Holineſs, Heavenlineſs, comforted, aſſur'd in Faith by the Ideas and Thoughts God raiſes up within the Soul: but the publick Show or Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance a Believer makes by his profeſs'd Subjection to every Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Chriſt's Appointment, is to edify others. God makes Men Lights, to be ſet in Candleſticks for others. Churches are ſet up out of Loyalty to Chriſt; but what is the End, but the Growth of one another, and the Converſion of Strangers? I ſhould ſay more than would be believ'd by Srangers, if I ſhould give account of this Woman's Charity to Souls; and as there was a Fulneſs with reſpect to the End, ſo to the Principle; tho harmleſs as a Dove, yet not like <hi>Ephraim,</hi> a <hi>ſilly Dove without Heart.</hi> Her Comfort under her Croſſes, her Conſtancy under Diſcouragements, her conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Subjection to Ordinances, in the World's Eſteem, and bulk of Profeſſors, too vile and contemptible, her Courage under Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, her Contentment under Circumſtances that would have fill'd hundreds with anxious Care, her Charity never abating upon Temptations from ſtraitning Difficulties at home, which at laſt her Faith may be ſaid to conquer more than her Pains, no Hypocrite
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:56657:17"/>could ever paint the Fruits of the Spirit, to ſuch a Life, Heat and Motion, never yet were drawn by any Pencil: Her Pulſe and Zeal, Warmth and Works, left no <hi>may be's</hi> in any Soul that had the Spirit of diſcerning. One of her Chriſtian Siſters had aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance without Clouds (tho with a moſt painful torturing Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per) 40 years together. Her own Life of Faith wanted neither Joy nor Peace. I wiſh that ſome poor Earth-worm, ſome cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous Miſer might lay to Heart the Eaſe and Pleaſure that conſiſts in being a faithful Steward; that the rampant Prodigal would conſider, that tho he may rebel, the Godly only doth rejoice. Theirs is like the crackling of Thorns under a Pot, a Noiſe not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry harmonious nor delightful; and the end is Aſhes: but the Joy of the Believer is all his Life, is in his Death; Death's Ghoſtly looks, his ſevere Blows, his tormenting Wracks, cannot imbitter this Cup of Joy: as I am inform'd it was with her; <hi>my Joy in the end, is Joy without end.</hi> This is another Ingredient of Fulneſs, a Fulneſs in degree, a Fulneſs of Joy, when all our Sorrow flows only from want of more Holineſs, when with <hi>Lot</hi> it's only from the Sins of the Sodomites we live among; our Tears with <hi>David</hi> are either becauſe the Wicked tranſgreſs the Law of God, or our own Infirmities prevail into Deformities. Conſider, O ſecure Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that every converted one is a Child of Light, begotten of the Father of Lights; and the Seed of Grace is a Seed of Light. Now the meaneſt Light in the World will diſpel Darkneſs from it ſelf, and in ſome meaſure communicate it to others: the Stars will ſparkle in the darkeſt Night, a Candle will conquer a large Room of Darkneſs; nay, the fainteſt Light of a dri'd or ſcaly Fiſh, or rotten Wood, will remain invincible againſt all the Power of Darkneſs: there is no Faith without ſome Aſſurance, nor no Grace without ſome ſecret Joy. If our Joy and our Hopes be in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene Air of Heaven, the Tempeſts below cannot extinguiſh it.</p>
            <p n="3">3ly. A following the Lord uniformly, and proportionably, is a fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the Lord fully. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.21. <hi>That thou obſerve all theſe things, without preferring one before another; and that thou do nothing partially.</hi> The new Creature is neither maim'd nor monſtrous; there is a comely Symmetry in a Chriſtian's Growth; all his Zeal and Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is not terminated on one Ordinance; according to the Weight and Moment of the Matters of the Law, they are of Value with him: he is no Phariſee to neglect the weightier Matters: he values an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:56657:18"/>in Chriſt above all: next an holy Life, he eſteems a Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion under all Marks of Chriſtianity, and is jealous of every other Mark, leſt it be the Beaſt's and Dragon's: he prefers a whole Set and Species of Precepts and Ordinances to the Mode of one, that may be debatable too. The Churches Hedg has many Stakes in it: the neglect of that is not the neglect of one Command, but of a whole Series, and the Means of quickning and giving Life to all.</p>
            <p n="4">4ly. A following the Lord fully, is to follow him in all Places and Times; whether the Company be for Truth or againſt it, they are for it, not imprudently caſting Pearls before Swine. But Truth is then like a Fire in the Breaſt, and a Flame ſhut up in the Bones, when derided and oppos'd; and when Seaſon requires, is defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and vindicated. Religion rules the Converſation in the Shop or Market, Court or Kitchin, as well as in Church, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſays <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in his Ethics. A <hi>Caleb</hi> is a true Cube; throw him where you will, he falls on a Square. True Gold waſtes not in the Fire, ruſts not in the Water. He is not a Phariſee, good in open view, nought in ſecret; nor of the vain Religion <hi>James</hi> ſpeaks of, that lies all in the Tongue, and yet not able to govern or ſteer that aright. He always minds an over-looking and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearing God; he fears continually, and his Faith and Love keep pace with his Fear.</p>
            <p n="5">5ly. A following the Lord fully conſiſts in a conſtant Deſire and Endeavour after a Fulneſs; fully and following after will conſiſt (without repugnancy) in no other ſenſe. We find the Angels following after Knowledg, prying and ſearching into Divine My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries; and we read of them rejoicing in their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>'s, I have found him, I have found him, 4000 Years after their Creations at leaſt, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3. And ſhall the Angels in the triumphing Church above run to and fro for the Increaſe of Knowledg, and the Angels below ſtand at a ſtay, and ſay, it is enough? Did the Prophets in the Old Teſtament, ſearch into Brim and Bottom, Time and Place, Manner and Matter of their own Prophecies, and ſhall not we? A thriving Miniſtry would make a thriving People, and a thriving People would make a diligent Miniſtry. Do not cry to your Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, Pray preach eaſy things, and ſmooth things: do not ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy your ſelves only with old repeated things, when it's the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Chriſt that the Scribe be Learned, and able to bring forth New and Old. Make your Paſtors live without Care, in caring
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:56657:18"/>for them in worldly things, that their Care may be alone ſpent in providing Food for your Souls. It is not to be told in <hi>Gath</hi> what Graſhopers we are in compariſon of our Fathers, by this very thing. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1. how pathetically does <hi>Paul</hi> exhort the converted Hebrews to leave the Principles of the Doctrine of Chriſt, and go on to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection? Is there not ſome Truth in the falſe Calumnies of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane, who ſpend their Sabbaths in the Fields, Beds, or Taverns; who ſay, <hi>We can tell all that we ſhall hear at Church,</hi> we know more than we can do? But new Arguments might make them believe that more firmly; and if they believ'd what they pretend to know, their Faith would make a new Life. Did they believe that the Lord is good to thoſe that wait on him, and to the Soul that ſeeketh him, they would not ſlight ſuch a gainful Trade. Let us then through Hearing, Reading, Praying, and Meditating, follow on to know more fully, to believe more fully: Let our Faith grow more ſtable and fix'd at the Root, by clear Evidence and powerful Arguments, water'd with the Dew of Heaven, until it come to a Demonſtration of the Spirit, and full Aſſurance of Faith: Let it be like the ſpreading Vine, ſtretching it ſelf, and by its <hi>tendrel</hi> Fingers laying hold of every Promiſe: Let it flouriſh in Comforts, and fructify like the Cluſters of <hi>Eſhcol,</hi> that were planted by the upper and nether Springs: To have a more full and perfect Patience, until we are capable to poſſeſs our Souls, and our Souls poſſeſs us in Want and Wearineſs, in Reproach and Flattery, that the things of the World, and Perſons too, may ſtill be an <hi>Obiter</hi> in Compariſon: To have a more full Practice, do not ſay like <hi>Balaam, Let me die the Death of the Righteous;</hi> come, let us live their Life, a holy Life, a penitential Life, a ſelf-deny'd Life, a Life not like others: The World's Cuſtom and Courſe is the high way to Hell; <hi>If we do his Will, then ſhall we know the Doctrine.</hi> But let us look to the Earth's excellent Ones, its few Names who forget all that is paſt, and count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Victories over Temptations already attain'd nothing, the Knowledg nothing, Diligence nothing, and therefore they preſſed on to what was before; never, with <hi>Laodicea,</hi> crying, <hi>I am rich, and full, and need nothing:</hi> no, the Bleſſing is to them that hunger and thirſt. This is to follow the Lord fully, to grow in Grace, and in the Knowledg of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, to pierce the Sun with Eagles Eyes, and ſoar towards him with Eagles Wings.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, A feeling Senſe of our Defectiveneſs; this neceſſarily
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:56657:19"/>flows from the former. Who will ever follow hard after what he feels no want of? Will ever the Man that thinks he knows all the Scriptures, cry out at a new Diſcovery, <hi>I rejoice at thy Word as one that findeth great Spoil?</hi> Pſal. 119. or under Darkneſs and Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, <hi>Lord, teach thou me thy Statutes, make me underſtand thy Law?</hi> No, <hi>he flattereth himſelf in his own Eyes, and refuſeth to underſtand.</hi> He that ſees not his own Sin as odious and troubleſome as the Burden of a Twin-Carcaſe already dead, will never cry out, <hi>Who will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver me from this Body of Death?</hi> It is a true Saying of a Bluſh, that it is <hi>malae Cauſae bonum Signum;</hi> or, as <hi>Homer</hi> phraſes it, an honeſt Heart has a weak Forehead. He that is acquainted with the Deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of his own Heart, is jealous he may be guilty, he is conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of ſo much Guilt; <hi>Is it I, Lord? is it I?</hi> ſays every honeſt Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple. <hi>O let my Heart be upright in thy Statutes!</hi> ſays an upright <hi>David;</hi> and elſewhere, <hi>When thou takeſt away the wicked like Droſs, my Fleſh trembles for fear of thee, and I am horribly afraid of thy Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> When Men can look back on their Sins, as <hi>Lombard</hi>'s Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on her three Baſtards, with Pleaſure (ſhe could not repent of the Act which had ſuch brave Effects and Fruits) it is very ſad; and forward on their Duties like Dreamers, who find flying as eaſy as walking; it is very dangerous. <hi>Heal me, for I have ſinned, my Bones are broken with it; help me, for I am weak,</hi> is the Language of him who follows the Lord fully.</p>
            <p>I come now to the ſecond Part of the Text, the <hi>Reward,</hi> and 5th Member in the Subdiviſion propoſed for a General Head: <hi>Him will I bring into the Land whereinto he went.</hi> Here is a poor indigent <hi>Jacob</hi> travelling with his Staff in his Hand, and a Stone for his Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, made two, nay twenty Troops. Here is a mean <hi>Caleb,</hi> (not all Heart, as <hi>Fuller</hi> ſays, for then it would be <hi>Calleb</hi>) mean in Name, mean in Birth, the youngeſt of three, mean in Poſſeſſion, mean in Place, a Spy: he has firſt gotten his Portion carved out to him, and a large one too, ſeveral Cities, ſeveral Kingdoms, <hi>Hebron</hi> one, <hi>Debir</hi> one, <hi>Bethlehem</hi> one; the very Poſſeſſions of old <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> the Oaks of <hi>Mamre,</hi> and the Wells of the South, <hi>viz. Iſaac</hi>'s, are all his, and the Title the beſt in the World, he holds of none but God: but in Gratitude, or by way of quit-rent, he gives the Prieſts a large Share with him. Here is a great Leſſon for Men advanced from Poverty to Riches, a low Eſtate to Honour,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:56657:19"/>a private <hi>Caleb</hi> to be the greateſt Prince of <hi>Judah,</hi> nay the greateſt Part of <hi>Judah</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">I find the Body of the Tribe of <hi>Judah</hi> came of him by this Calculation, <hi>Judah</hi> had but two Sons, <hi>Pharez</hi> and <hi>Zerah,</hi> who had any Poſterity. 2ly. <hi>Pharez</hi> had but two Sons, <hi>Hezron</hi> and <hi>Hamul;</hi> and <hi>Hamul</hi> had no Poſterity. 3ly. <hi>Hezron</hi> had but three Sons, the third was <hi>Caleb:</hi> in ſhort, by Birth he was the tenth Part, or at leaſt the twelfth Part, as <hi>Judah</hi> was of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> But then half of theſe were cut off, when all above twenty Years of Age were cut off. 2ly. A 10th part were cut off, when <hi>Achor</hi> the Troubler of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was deſtroyed: and this may be further confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the Genealogies of his Offſpring, containing more Families than all the Tribe of <hi>Judah</hi> beſide.</note>; for it was his Inheritance, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 30.14. <hi>We made an Invaſion upon the South of the Cherethites</hi> (i. e. Philiſtins) <hi>upon that of it which belonged to</hi> Judah, <hi>or which is the South of</hi> Caleb. Indeed his elder Brother <hi>Ram,</hi> or <hi>Aram,</hi> got the Honour of the Crown, <hi>David</hi>'s Line came from that Root; yet <hi>Caleb</hi> wanted not the Honour to have Judges of <hi>Iſrael</hi> of his Poſterity, even in his own Day, <hi>Othniel</hi> his Son-in-law. It was not the firſt time the younger Brother became the better Man for Time, and Eternity too: but the Leſſon we are taught, is not to forget our Original, and to remember it came through the gracious Promiſes, not merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Purchaſe or Birth-right; to remember, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 113.7. <hi>that he raiſeth up the Poor out of the Duſt, and lifteth the Needy out of the Dunghil, that he may ſet him with Princes:</hi> To remember the Pit out of which we were digged, and the Rock from whence hewen. This might be a great Remedy to ſome Peoples haughty Spirits, their inſolent Looks towards their own Fleſh and Blood, their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perious ſcornful Carriage towards others, not long ago their Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, if not Superiours or Supporters, leſt they hear of God as <hi>Saul, When thou waſt mean I advanced thee:</hi> he had better have kept Aſſes all his Days, than to have been a King: his End was lower than before; ſo will be thine, pitiful, not pitied, the Subject of Miſery, and Object of Mockery, miſerable without Commiſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, envied now, and odious then, if Humility of Mind attend not the Advancement of thy Condition, and a faithful Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thy Stewardſhip. If I had Room for Inlargement, there are here two Rivulets (like the Brook <hi>Bezors,</hi> that encompaſs the moſt fertil Land of <hi>Caleb</hi>) or Subjects that meet in my Text: one is the Pregnancy of the Promiſe, the Bountifulneſs of the Bleſſing: The 2d is the Proportion or Sutableneſs to the Work
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:56657:20"/>and Actions to which they were promiſed; there was an Identity and Sameneſs in it, <hi>Into the Land whereinto he went.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the firſt, the South of <hi>Judah</hi> was a rich Inheritance; <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Benjamin</hi> poſſeſſed the Royalties and Dominions of fifteen Kings; there were but 31 Royolets of all, his Share was largeſt; and as <hi>Sandys</hi> ſays in his Travels, the moſt fruitful ſtill of all <hi>Canaan,</hi> if not of all the World, are the Valleys and Banks of <hi>Bezor.</hi> Now when God has made a fruitful Land barren for the Wickedneſs of them that dwell therein, <hi>Caleb</hi>'s Countrey remains the Monument of what it was before the Curſe. It is ſaid, Num. 13.23. <hi>That it was a Land that eateth up its Inhabitants;</hi> but ſo fertil it was they could not eat it up, the Goodneſs of the Land engaged them to fight for it. The Deſarts of <hi>Judea</hi> were like Engliſh Parks, and the Hills like big Bellies, pregnant with Minerals, Salt-peter, Braſs, Iron, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the Surface covered with the ſtreight Cedars, ſtrong Oaks, ſhady Palms, and ſweet Firs, or more fruitful Trees; and their Valleys enriched with all things uſeful. The greateſt Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is about Water, ſince the Jews Wells were in the Tops of their Houſes; on which account ſome deny it poſſible to have dipped the Eunuch between <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and <hi>Gaza</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Acts 8.36, 26. <hi>As they went on their way,</hi> viz. in the Road between <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> and <hi>Gaza, they came unto</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, aliquid Aquae, <hi>ſome Water:</hi> The Journey was 24 Miles. The Queſtion is, whether there was in that Road ſufficient Water for the Purpoſe? They confirm the Objection with this, that <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> who needed much Water to the legal way, went to <hi>Jordan</hi> to baptize, when he preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this Countrey. I anſwer, 1ſt. That the Land, <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.7. <hi>was a Land of Brooks and Fountains:</hi> and though no Land is more narrowly ſearched into by Choro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphers than it, yet there might be a Place in 24 Miles fit for the Purpoſe, that is neither in our Maps nor Hiſtories. 2ly. They do mention many not far out of his Road: it is true <hi>Iſaac</hi>'s Wells were further South beyond <hi>Gaza,</hi> and ſome Miles out of the Road; and the Well of <hi>Siriah,</hi> fatal to brave <hi>Abner,</hi> was too much weſtward, nor had they been proper: as far Weſt were the Brook of <hi>Jeruel,</hi> and the Fiſh-Pools of <hi>Hebron.</hi> But the Eunuch kept the ſtreight Road, he drove not out of the Way. 3ly. I will then find you three Brooks in this little Journey; firſt the River of the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtins, that roſe about 2 or 3 Miles from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> about the Rock <hi>Bethzur,</hi> or Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley of <hi>Rephaim,</hi> where the Angel was heard on the Top of the Mulberry Trees; this River was ſo big, that it made a conſiderable Stop between the Armies of the Pagans and Iſraelites in the time of the Maccabees: Now though his Road was by the Head of it, yet there were many Pools in that Place, from thence called <hi>Baca,</hi> Pſal. 84.6. mentioned in no Hiſtory, <hi>who paſſing through the Valley of</hi> Baca, &amp;c. But it may be thought here was too little Space from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> for a Chariot and Six, to preach a Sermon in; and 2ly, may be <hi>Bezor</hi> was too far off, being the River that <hi>Gaza</hi> ſtood on. We will then fix on <hi>Sorek,</hi> or <hi>Eſheol,</hi> that came into it, or ſome Spring about the Head of it, which was in <hi>Caleb</hi>'s Territories too, which would render it both poſſible and probable. But the Matter of Fact is ſtruck down by two Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, holy, good, honeſt Men, who lived next to that Age, of any Teſtimony we have, who could not be impoſed on as to the Circumſtances of the Water, the one living at <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> the other at <hi>Caeſarea,</hi> both on the Confines of the Place. The Perſons are <hi>Euſebius</hi> and <hi>Jerome:</hi> their Teſtimony is this; their Deſign is the Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rography of the Land; their Words in effect agree, and are thus in Engliſh: <q>
                     <hi>Bethſoron</hi> is a Village as we go from <hi>Aelia</hi> (i. e. <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>) to <hi>Hebron</hi> in the 20th Stone (<hi>i. e.</hi> two Miles from <hi>Hebron</hi>) juſt by which there is a Spring at the Roots of the Mountain, that is ſipped up by the ſame Ground out of which it bubbles, or boils forth: here was the Eunuch (the great Miniſter of State to Queen <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dace</hi>) baptized by <hi>Philip.</hi>
                  </q> She was blind of an Eye; it were well for ſome they were blind of both, to have ſuch Spectacles: She was another <hi>Elizabeth</hi> for Love to and from her Subjects, and Eſteem from others even a <hi>Tiberius.</hi> The beſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture I can make is, that it was <hi>Enhakkore, Judg.</hi> 15.19. where <hi>Sampſon</hi> was refreſh'd with Water: Circumſtances agree, for they were very nigh, if not the ſame. 2ly. <hi>Philip</hi> was carried to <hi>Aſhdod</hi> down the River, as <hi>Sampſon</hi> came up from it to that Place.</note>. But if it had been 10
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:56657:20"/>times better, nay all <hi>Canaan</hi> his, it had not contained Fulneſs enough to make up <hi>Caleb</hi>'s Inheritance; the Typicalneſs of the Land, the Temper of his Mind, the Fulneſs of his following God, beſpeaks God to be his God, and Heaven to be his home; all <hi>Canaan,</hi> all <hi>Adam</hi>'s Paradiſe juſt by, on <hi>Jordan</hi> or <hi>Euphrates,</hi> was but a Picture, a Map of this: nay, all the World, and all the World in its Spring ſplit, new drawn by infinite Art, is but a Shadow of the Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the Saints in Light, Saints in Love, Saints in Reſt: How elſe could <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed by Faith be Heirs of the World? Rom. 4.13. <hi>The Promiſe that he ſhould be Heir of the World — was to him and his Seed, through the Righteouſneſs of Faith? I. R.</hi> thus. The World was <hi>Adam</hi>'s and his Seed, but was forefaulted by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion; this Forfeiture is taken off through Faith in Chriſt, which Redemption coſt him ſo dear, that it's called a new Purchaſe, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.14. <hi>World</hi> then muſt either be taken for all the Earth as a Type of Heaven, or rather comprehending all its ſeveral Globes: our Bodies, after glorified, may as eaſily paſs from one Globe to another as now from one Houſe to another to make a Viſit. <hi>Caleb</hi> had Right to <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Promiſe, that is, the World; he was a Son of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and my Parallel a Daughter of <hi>Abraham.</hi> For Application, I ſhall on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet <hi>Caleb</hi>'s beſt Privileges in this Life and yours together, not only
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:56657:21"/>his Land but Iſraelitiſh State, to whom belonged the Oracles, the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, the Promiſes and Covenant, or Church-Privileges, all which highly advance the Price of <hi>Caleb</hi>'s Portion: as to the other Life, it is one to Believers in both Old and New-Teſtament-State (except the Progreſs they have made by being in Heaven ſo long before us, ſets them in a higher Form) they looked for another City than <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> one that had better Foundations, tho all true living Rock, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.14. and another Countrey than <hi>Canaan:</hi> they were Pilgrims even in <hi>Canaan,</hi> they deſired a better Country, that is an Heavenly, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.16. To preſs to <hi>Caleb</hi>'s Spirit and Practice from this, is ſo big, I cannot ſpeak what becomes it; Faith is ſo weak, it appears at a great Diſtance, and therefore little. In ſhort, my Uſe is this, We are more obliged to be full in our following God, than <hi>Caleb</hi> was from his temporal Portion, Eſtate, Church-State, Politick State. 1ſt. It's the Subſtance that is in our Expectation, the Shadow and Type was immediately in his. 2ly. Forty Years was he to wander in the Wilderneſs before he ſet one Foot upon the Land: I could never ſee from the true Canons of Chronology, Scripture or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, any Ground to countenance the Prophecy of 1697; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed this is truly 1699, but yet I cannot think we ſhall continue 40 Years in the Wilderneſs. 3ly. Our preſent Circumſtances are full of Straits, Want of Trade, Money, full of Fears, aſſaulted with a powerful Enemy, no Appearance of Victory, Diſtreſs in our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, abounding Sin and Judgments. but <hi>I. R.</hi> was it worſe than theirs in the Wilderneſs? All ſecond Cauſes againſt them, and their Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage, under the Commination of God to deſtroy them all, before theſe Years were at an End, or they ſee the Land of Promiſe. 4ly. Compare their Means of Salvation with ours, their Light and Hope of Salvation with ours, and our Condition is not only better than their Wilderneſs-Condition, but better than their State under a triumphant <hi>David,</hi> or a peaceful <hi>Solomon:</hi> for (1.) We have the Exhibition, and the Hiſtory of that Perfect Righteouſneſs, that Everlaſting Righteouſneſs, that Eternal and Plentiful Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that they could only look at in a Prophecy, and it may be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand as little as we do of his glorious Reign, when he ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear the ſecond Time without Sin. (2.) We have a full Remiſſion of Sin; their Remiſſion was a kind of Pretermiſſion, or Preteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Sin, which (<hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25.) is called <hi>the Forbearance of God.</hi> The Difference ſeems to lie in theſe things: 1ſt. The Price was not
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:56657:21"/>yet paid. 2ly. The ſame Sins for which they had offered Sacrifice were brought to their Remembrance again by new Sacrifices, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying their not being in a conſtant State of Favour with God: hence their Conſciences did perpetually accuſe them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.2. and their Fears torment them. 3ly. They were under a Typical Curſe for non-obſervance of ſome Ceremonial Law, which was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt impoſſible to obſerve: but under the New Teſtament there is no kind of Condemnation to them that are in Chriſt, there is no more Sacrifice for Sin; which imports Divine Juſtice to be fully ſatisfied, Divine Wrath fully appeaſed; all things are ready, and we are invited to the Marriage-Feaſt. Remiſſion in this full Emphatick Senſe, is promiſed as the Due of the New Teſtament, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.34. and hiſtoriſed as its Privilege, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.14. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.22. Chriſt to us is a full Surety, an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Fidejuſſor, &amp; Expromiſſor:</hi> hence Believers under the New Teſtament, who grow in Grace and Knowledg, enjoy a more perfected, tranquil, ſecure and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Conſcience; though thro Backſlidings they ſometimes doubt if they be the Men, but doubt not about the Validity and Accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs of the Sacrifice. 4ly. Our Light is much more clear, our Vail is thinner, and our Stile more familiar: the Contrivance of Divine Wiſdom in the Salvation of Man is more perſpicuouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, ſince he who was from Eternity in the Boſom of the Father, is become a Preacher of it, <hi>I will declare thy Name unto my Brethren, I have made known thy Name unto them.</hi> A 5th Advantage is the Manner of teaching, by Effuſion of the Holy Spirit on the Hearts of Men, to convince of Sin, Righteouſneſs and Judgment: this is the Goſpel's Glory, this makes Believers Chriſt's Epiſtles, this makes our Subjection to all his Ordinances a willing Obedience. We ſee a Reaſon for it, as well as Authority for it, which renders all our Service a reaſonable Service, even the ſevereſt bearing of the Croſs. The Difference is ſo great, that our State eminently is called the State of Faith, Gal. 3.23. <hi>After that Faith is come,</hi> and before that Faith was. Their State is a State of Hope, <hi>By Hope we are ſaved:</hi> for Chriſt who was the Hope of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and whom they looked at as future and to come, is preſent to our Faith: we hope for eternal Life through him, but we believe in him as already having given Satisfaction, and now ſitting at the right Hand of God, our Interceſſor: It may be on this account we are call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed perfect, they Children in Chriſt. A 6th Advantage is the Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:56657:22"/>between their Church-State and ours. I do humbly conceive that in many places where two Covenants are mentioned, the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference is not between the Covenant of Works under the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> and the Covenant of Grace, but between the Church-Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant under the Law, and under the Goſpel: by the former all that were of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> were of the Church, they came in by Generation and Birth; the ſecond Covenant-Conſtitution requires Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: the former filled the Church with profane Perſons, and therefore required a rigid Yoak, ſevere Diſcipline, frequent Ejecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; the other is more holy and Heaven-like. Church-Members are more like Sons having a Spirit and Air of Liberty; they had Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of their Fleſh, who chaſtiſed them at pleaſure; we own no Paſtour to have paternal Authority, that is, to chaſtiſe at Pleaſure: <hi>Call no Man your Father upon Earth, for one is your Father which is in Heaven,</hi> and <hi>one your Maſter even Chriſt;</hi> hence frequently Chriſt forbids to imitate the Gentile Lordſhip in his Kingdom, and the Apoſtles to exerciſe Lordſhip over God's Inheritance.</p>
            <p>How powerful ſhould theſe Motives be to undertake his light Burden and eaſy Yoak, to follow him fully in every Ordinance of his Inſtitution, to follow the Lamb whitherſoever he leads us, to bear whatever Croſs his Providence impoſes?</p>
            <p>But yet the 2d thing is the more native Subject of this part of the Text, the Correſpondency, Proportion, or Identity, between the Work and Reward; what he ventured for, he ſhall enjoy. <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> makes the true Moral of it, <hi>The Backſlider in Heart ſhall be fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with his own ways, and a good Man ſhall be ſatisfied from himſelf.</hi> If there be not a heavenlineſs in a Man's Temper before he die, his Hope may deceive him in expecting it then. <hi>They that plough Iniquity, and ſow Wickedneſs, reap the ſame: but the Righteous ſhall eat the Fruit of his Doings.</hi> Sin and Hell, Holineſs and Heaven, agree like Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception and Birth; <hi>When Luſt hath conceived, it bringeth forth Sin, and Sin when 'tis finiſhed brings forth Death:</hi> as hatred to God unfits for obedience to God, ſo it incapacitates to enjoy God. Can he that has Enmity of God in his Heart, take pleaſure in the Fruition of his Company? Is not the Place of Darkneſs moſt ſutable to them that love Darkneſs rather than Light? Is it a cruel Sentence for God to ſay, <hi>Depart from me,</hi> to them whoſe Souls ſay to God, <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from us?</hi> When Chriſt has long importuned us to uſe him as our Advocate and Reconciler, is it harſh to ſay, I will not ſpeak
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:56657:22"/>a word for you? If the Spirit of God hath ſtriven with us, 20, 30 Years in our Conſciences, and under Ordinances, Will his leaving of us be unjuſt? Or is it unmerciful to leave us, when we have ſo long grieved him, vex'd him and provoked him? When a Man's natural Temper is being dead to God, and alive to the World, is it not natural for that native Temper to grow more compleat and perfect? and what is Hell but the Perfection? <hi>Poiret</hi> reckons it to be the eaſieſt Rule of Government, and the firſt Rule of Juſtice, to let every Man have what he will. O Sinner! conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Hell is thy choice; the worſt Sentence at the Day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is to let thee have thy Liking: thou likeſt not Believers Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, nor Church-Communion; thou ſhalt have the Company of them thou didſt like: thou preferreſt the Tyranny of Satan to the Government of God; the Law of Sin is writ in thy Heart, not the Law of God; thou ſhalt have thy Choice. Conſider, Sinner, it's thy own Doings that dries thee, and renders thee combuſtible to the Flames of Divine Wrath; thy Hell is begun already, thou woundeſt thy Conſcience now, it only ſmarts more by a never-dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Worm there; now thy Paſſions maſter thee, their Dominion only will be more tyrannical: thou art uneaſy now with a never-ſatisfied Deſire, it will then only crave more cruelly, like a Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture eating out thy Heart: thou envieſt the Proſperity of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly now, it ſhall be only then in Maturity; thou wilt not hope now, thou ſhalt but then deſpair.</p>
            <p>The ſame Relation lies between Grace and Glory, that lies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Sin and Hell. Love is fully as much the Principle of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and Fruition, as Hatred is of Rebellion and ſpiritual Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. <hi>Light is ſown for the Righteous, and Joy for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright in Heart.</hi> Faith and Viſion differ only as the Seed and Shock of Corn: Grace is the Father's drawing of the Heart to himſelf; There is none in Heaven and Earth (ſaith the Soul) that I deſire but thee; Thou ſhalt have me, ſaith the Sentence of the Judg. I ſhall leave the reſt to thy Meditation; only conſider, that in all the typical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> there is nothing ſeems ſo ſutable to typify the Identity between Work and Reward, the Temper of Mind in time, and the Conſummation of it in Eternity, as <hi>Caleb</hi>'s having the very ſame Land he ſpied out, and contended for.</p>
            <p>The 6th and laſt Head is the Entail of the Promiſe: <hi>His Seed ſhall
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:56657:23"/>poſſeſs it.</hi> This, if we take without an Emphaſis, is no more than what is promiſed to the reſt, that their Seed ſhould poſſeſs the Land: indeed if we, take it in Conjunction, that both he and they ſhould, then the Emphaſis is ſpoken to before, for it lies in his poſſeſſion of it. But Promiſes are uſually from a God very preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant things; and I am under Apprehenſions that there will be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd Mountains of Divine Goodneſs, both as to Extent and Intenſeneſs in Promiſes, that we look on as Mole-hills: it's like then a diſtinguiſhing and ſingular length of Time and Number of Generations is implied in it; which we may thus confirm, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies of <hi>Jabez</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Vatablus</hi> thinks that <hi>Jabez</hi> and <hi>Othniel</hi> were the ſame, and (may be <hi>Hezron</hi> and <hi>Jephunne</hi> the ſame, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 2.9, 18, 24, 42, 50. &amp; 4.15. <hi>Num.</hi> 13.6. &amp; 14.6, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) others a very near Relation (I confeſs theſe Genealogies are yet too diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult for me to be poſitive in, and ſo this Subject of Entail: <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. the Apoſtle ſays, there are Myſteries in it, Depths of Wiſdom and Knowledg) from <hi>Jabez</hi> come the <hi>Rechabites,</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 2.55. It is true, ſome count the <hi>Rechabites, Kenites;</hi> I find no convincing Reaſon for it, nor for this, that all called <hi>Kenites</hi> ſhould be from <hi>Jethro, Moſes</hi>'s Father in Law, for 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 27.10. one Family of that Name was in <hi>Caleb</hi>'s Portion, and he (<hi>Joſh.</hi> 14.6.) is called a <hi>Kenezite,</hi> more of kindred ſurely with the <hi>Kenites</hi> than with the curſed <hi>Kenezites, Gen.</hi> 15. (ſooner ripe for Ruin than his Neighbours) or <hi>Kenezites</hi> of <hi>Edom.</hi> The <hi>Kenites</hi> of <hi>Hobab</hi> dwelt elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, <hi>Judg.</hi> 4.17. &amp; 1.16. <hi>viz.</hi> in <hi>Naphtali</hi> and <hi>Jericho,</hi> and 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.6. among the Amalekites.</note> came of <hi>Caleb,</hi> and the Rechabites came of <hi>Jabez,</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 2.55. We find them of great Note in <hi>Jehu</hi>'s Reign for Intereſt and Piety, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 10.15. he was <hi>Jehu</hi>'s Miniſter of State, as far as his Reformation went; theſe were the Men he flatter'd with that Saying, <hi>Come, ſee my Zeal for the Lord.</hi> We find them in <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi>'s time conſtant and zealous in their Piety, <hi>Jer.</hi> 35.11. and then this Promiſe of Entail, when it had laſted about 1000 Years, is repeated with a more powerful Emphaſis than before, <hi>Jer.</hi> 35.19. Jonadab, <hi>the Son of</hi> Rechab, <hi>ſhall not want a Man to ſtand before me for ever.</hi> The Fruits of former entail'd Grace have begotten Promiſes of greater Grace: it is not a Promiſe of Office in the Prieſthood, that was not to ſtand for ever, but a Place within the Church of God. How it is this Day fulfilled, when neither Jew nor Gentile can give account of their Families for any conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable time (a few being excepted) the God who can diſtinguiſh the Duſt of every Individual at the Reſurrection, only knows; no doubt theſe Springs that run under ground inviſible to Man, will then be ſet forth in harmonious Lines and lively Colours. There
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:56657:23"/>is an Entail of a Curſe from the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> and an Entail of a Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from the Second, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. Among all the Entails by Promiſe or Covenant, that of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s ſeems to have the moſt Variety of Branches, ſome Spiritual, ſome Eccleſiaſtick, ſome Earthly, ſome by natural Generation, ſome by Ingrafture, and the moſt Turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and Windings, the moſt Interruptions and Breaches ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently, and yet the Tenor and Title the moſt fix'd and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.28. <hi>As concerning the Goſpel they are Enemies, but as touching Election, they are belov'd for the Fathers.</hi> It's no wonder that the 70 Years Captivity, which made the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> a <hi>Loammi,</hi> not my People in reſpect of the National Covenant at <hi>Sinai,</hi> could not violate the Family-Covenant of <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gal. 3. ſince this ſad Deſolation for 1500 Years upon that People has not drawn the Spirit and Fatneſs of that Root dry. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.16. <hi>If the Root</hi> (that one <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſays <hi>Jac. Alt. in Loc.</hi>) be holy, ſo the Branches, <hi>ver.</hi> 17, 26, 29. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. A thouſand Generations are not yet come; there were but about 54 from <hi>Abraham</hi> to Chriſt, not above 200 to this Day, <hi>Lev.</hi> 26.42, 44. That Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant will bring them out of this Diſtreſs. It is the common Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Men under the Name <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> that one part of that Promiſe's Fatneſs is, that this Root's Boughs bear Twigs or ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler Branches, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.39. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. but that I ſhall forbear, for the ſincere Love (in the Sight of God) I bear to them of another Opinion, of whom this pious Matron and Mother of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was. I confeſs I have heard many of them blam'd for idolizing this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of Profeſſors Baptiſm only, and placing all their Religion in it; but I muſt profeſs, to the Honour of this good Woman, and all them of my acquaintance (excepting ſome very few whoſe ſpiritual Baptiſm my Charity can ſcarce reach, as I may ſay the like of ſome of every Denomination) I never did obſerve any ſuch Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, but on the contrary a moſt facile and eaſy bearing their
<note n="*" place="bottom">The Story is no Secret: When the Ship of exil'd Scots came into this River, ſhe with others carried them Proviſion, and ſhow'd to them other Kindneſſes, even to their Redemption: When ſhe ask'd if they knew of whom they receiv'd this Brotherly Love? their Anſwer was, No doubt true Brethren and Siſters, as they had reaſon to judg from what they experienced. Her reply, or another's with her, was, <hi>We are all Anabaptiſts.</hi> The reſt of the Story I leave to Tradition, which did ſhow how eaſily ſhe could bear being contemn'd and deſpis'd for her Profeſſion, even by them ſhe reliev'd, and reliev'd when a long Sufferer her ſelf, her Husband be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Sufferer, and driven from his Employ and Vocation, which was the Staff of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Family: <hi>Sed haec meminiſſe juvabit. Patitur, patietur, qui pari c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>egit.</hi>
               </note> Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:56657:24"/>whoſe Zeal on the contrary exceeded Knowledg.</p>
            <p>But I have exceeded the Bulk of Diſcourſes uſual of this kind, and waſted my Strength thorow Shortneſs of Time, and Smalneſs of Health. But I ſhould glory in all, if I could raiſe up, or awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken one <hi>Caleb,</hi> one to be firſt (<hi>Numb.</hi> 13.30.) in ſtopping our run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning back towards <hi>Egypt,</hi> disbelieving and deſpiſing the precious Promiſes and pleaſant Land, to be a <hi>Lot</hi> in our <hi>Sodom,</hi> a <hi>Noah</hi> in our Day, a <hi>Nicodemus</hi> outed of his worldly Policy, or a <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea</hi> ſhewing himſelf for a crucified Chriſt: and where there is any ſuch Temper, I would beg <hi>Caleb</hi>'s Perſeverance, that they would not take in evil part the Temper of their Brethren, that would rather ſtone them than reward them. <hi>Caleb</hi> met with no better, nor <hi>Luther</hi> in <hi>Saxony,</hi> nor <hi>Zuinglius</hi> in <hi>Helvetia,</hi> nor <hi>Huſs</hi> in <hi>Bohemia.</hi> Conſider, a Primacy and Perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity in Reward, requires a Primacy and Conſtancy in acting for God. O to be firſt, and to be full too in following God, is a great Reward in it ſelf! We can chalk out many Men firſt in ſuch and ſuch a Sin, one in Knavery, another in Idolatry, a 3d in Hypocriſy, and a 4th with the Daughters of <hi>Zion</hi> in Vanity, a 5th in Treachery; <hi>Joh.</hi> 19.11. <hi>He that delivered me unto thee, hath the greater Sin.</hi> The Spies firſt in Sin ſhall die firſt of the Plague, <hi>Num.</hi> 14.37. but whom God will make the firſt Inſtrument in <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi>'s Redemption, is yet in the dark. As we would make up a part of the two Witneſſes in the Wilderneſs, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. we ſhould follow <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Joſhua,</hi> who follow'd the Lord fully; they were the Witneſſes in their Day. When the Witneſſes Obedience is come to a Fulneſs, the Sins of the Amorites will be full too; 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.6. <hi>Having in a Readineſs to revenge all Diſobedience, when your Obedience is fulfilled.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="elegy">
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:56657:24"/>
            <head>In Remembrance of Mrs. <hi>CONSTANCY WARD.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>IF mournful Wiſhes of ten thouſand Hearts,</l>
               <l>Could have prevented or delay'd this Stroak:</l>
               <l>If Zeal and Vertue could <hi>WARD</hi> off the Darts</l>
               <l>Of Death, or could its dire Decrees revoke;</l>
               <l>Then conſtantly <hi>CONSTANTIA</hi> ſhould have liv'd,</l>
               <l>Of being dead, ſhould forthwith have reviv'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But the Almighty by a ſtated Law,</l>
               <l>Hath otherwiſe ordain'd, and every one</l>
               <l>Muſt to the Houſe of Silence once withdraw,</l>
               <l>There to attend a Reſurrection:</l>
               <l>And then <hi>CONSTANTIA</hi>'s bleſſed Soul ſhall be</l>
               <l>Rejoined to its
<note n="*" place="margin">Body.</note> 
                  <hi>WARD</hi> eternally.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now though her Death unto her ſelf be gain,</l>
               <l>The Loſs is great to poor ſurviving Saints,</l>
               <l>Who when diſtreſt did unto her complain,</l>
               <l>And were hid by her, and reliev'd in Wants:</l>
               <l>She with unwearied Pains did others move</l>
               <l>In Acts of Charity to ſhow their Love.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>She ſound Advice did give in terms moſt fit,</l>
               <l>Gentle Reproofs ſhe wiſely did convey,</l>
               <l>To ſolid Reaſons ſhe did ſtill ſubmit,</l>
               <l>Yielding always to Truth the Victory:</l>
               <l>And if in ſomething ſhe could not agree,</l>
               <l>She ſtill maintain'd a Chriſtian Charity.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>She labour'd much for Knowledg, and attain'd</l>
               <l>Degrees therein beyond her Sex, yet ſtill</l>
               <l>A deep Humility in her remain'd,</l>
               <l>A modeſt Carriage and complying Will:</l>
               <l>Her Faith and Hope were ſound, ſtrong, and ſincere,</l>
               <l>Her other Vertues all admired were.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:56657:25"/>
               <l>Her Troubles they were great, her Husband's Life</l>
               <l>To Tyrants Malice was deſign'd a Prey,</l>
               <l>And alſo ſhe the charitable Wife,</l>
               <l>From Popiſh Flames at laſt was forc'd to flee:</l>
               <l>All this Diſtreſs ſhe bore with <hi>Conſtancy,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With Silence and profound Humility.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>She hath obtain'd the Prize, her well-run Race</l>
               <l>Hath purchaſed to her on Earth Renown:</l>
               <l>Her Tears are now wip'd from her glorious Face,</l>
               <l>Her Temples circled with Salvation's Crown:</l>
               <l>Her Honour is with Jeſus Chriſt to reign,</l>
               <l>Her Work is ſtill to love, and ever ſing.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. K.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="acrostic">
            <head>An Acroſtick.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>Can thoſe who have ſurviv'd the bloody Rage</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Charles</hi> and <hi>James,</hi> acted on <hi>Britain</hi>'s Stage,</l>
               <l>Neglect to drop their Tears upon this Stone,</l>
               <l>Since underneath doth lie the Duſt of one,</l>
               <l>That while alive took pleaſure to ſupply,</l>
               <l>And hide ſuch as eſcap'd their Cruelty?</l>
               <l>No Difference in Judgment from her own,</l>
               <l>Could ever leſſen her Compaſſion:</l>
               <l>It flow'd to all alike; Scots Exiles were</l>
               <l>Equal with Engliſh, Objects of her Care.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Wiſdom and Knowledg, Zeal and Charity,</l>
               <l>Adorn'd her Life; now let her Memory</l>
               <l>Remain to future Ages, let her Praiſe</l>
               <l>Determin thee to imitate her Ways.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. K.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
